【音乐之声】
The Sound of Music - 1965
♪ 大地新象 ♪
♪ the hills are alive ♪
♪ 只因这天籁之声 ♪
♪ With the sound of music ♪
♪ 清歌传唱 ♪
♪ With songs they have sung ♪
♪ 千年万年 ♪
♪ For a thousand years ♪
♪ 云岭送翠 ♪
♪ the hills fill my heart ♪
♪ 只为这天籁之声 ♪
♪ With the sound of music ♪
♪ 我心雀跃不已 只因它拾得片音短曲 ♪
♪ My heart wants to sing every song it hears ♪
♪ 我心澎湃狂喜 宛如鸟生新羽展翅飞去 ♪
♪ My heart wants to beat like the wings of the birds that rise ♪
♪ 自湖滨遥向枝头高栖 ♪
♪ from the lake to the trees ♪
♪ 我心呢喃低语仿佛钟铃 ♪
♪ My heart wants to sigh Like a chime that flies ♪
♪ 自教堂乘风徐徐而来 ♪
♪ from a church on a breeze ♪
♪ 欢笑一如小溪清清 蜿蜒宛转 ♪
♪ To laugh like a brook When it trips and falls ♪
♪ 川流石头间 ♪
♪ Over stones on its way ♪
♪ 彻夜高歌 ♪
♪ To sing through the night ♪
♪ 就像云雀习祷 喜悦轻盈 ♪
♪ Like a lark who is learning to pray ♪
♪ 我总会来这山巅 ♪
♪ I go to the hills ♪
♪ 每当我心抑郁 ♪
♪ When my heart is lonely ♪
♪ 我知道定能听见 ♪
♪ I know I will hear ♪
♪ 昔日歌声 ♪
♪ What I've heard before ♪
♪ 我心将被赐福 ♪
♪ My heart will be blessed ♪
♪ 只因这天籁之音 ♪
♪ With the sound of music ♪
♪ 我也愿... ♪
♪ and I'll sing... ♪
♪ 再次高歌 ♪
♪ ...once more ♪
《真善美》
(奥地利 萨尔兹堡 30年代黄金时期)
♪ 哈利路亚 哈利路亚 ♪
♪ Hallelujah, hallelujah ♪
-院长 -柏尼丝修女
-Reverend Mother. -Sister Bernice.
-我找不到她 -玛丽亚
-I simply cannot find her. -Maria?
她又不见了
She's missing again.
也许我们该在她脖子上挂个牛铃
We should've put a cowbell around her neck.
你找过谷仓了吗？ 她很喜欢动物
Have you tried the barn? You know how much she adores the animals.
我到处都找过了
I have looked everywhere. In all of the usual places.
我建议你
Sister, considering it's Maria...
找不寻常的地方
...I suggest you look in someplace unusual.
院长
Well, Reverend Mother...
我希望这次违规
...I hope this new infraction ends whatever doubts...
会结束你对她在这里会有未来的疑虑
...you may still have about Maria's future here.
我对疑虑仍常保持信心
I always try to keep faith in my doubts, Sister Berthe.
毕竟黑羊的毛也是会温暖
After all, the wool of a black sheep is just as warm.
我们不是争论绵羊颜色
We are not talking about sheep, black or white, Sister Margaretta.
所有修女的候选人中她最槽
Of all the candidates for the novitiate, Maria is the least--
各位...
Children, children.
我们想了解在修道院的人表现如何
We were speculating about the qualifications of our postulants.
见习修女和修道院修女的主管
The Mistress of Novices and the Mistress of Postulants...
表达了不同的意见来协助我
...were trying to help me by expressing opposite points of view.
凯萨琳修女 告诉我 你懧为玛丽亚如何？
Tell me, Sister Catherine, what do you think of Maria?
她是个好女孩 有的时候
She's a wonderful girl, some of the time.
-阿葛莎修女？ -玛丽亚讨人喜欢
-Sister Agatha? -It's very easy to like Maria...
除了不讨人喜欢的时候
...except when it's difficult.
-苏菲亚修女 你呢？ -我喜欢她
-And you, Sister Sophia? -Oh, I love her very dearly.
但她爱惹麻烦
But she always seems to be in trouble, doesn't she?
这就是我要说的
Exactly what I say.
♪ 她会爬树伤膝盖 ♪
♪ She climbs a tree and scrapes her knee ♪
♪ 衣服裂开 ♪
♪ Her dress has got a tear ♪
♪ 在作弥撒的路上吹口哨 ♪
♪ She waltzes on her way to Mass and whistles on the stair ♪
♪ 帽巾下 头发内会有发卷 ♪
♪ and underneath her wimple She has curlers in her hair ♪
♪ 她常常在修道院内唱歌 ♪
♪ I've even heard her singing ln the abbey ♪
♪ 她总是迟到作祷告 ♪
♪ She's always late for chapel ♪
♪ 可是忏悔却出自真心 ♪
♪ But her penitence is real ♪
♪ 她做什么都迟到 ♪
♪ She's always late for everything ♪
♪ 但每餐饭从不迟到 ♪
♪ Except for every meal ♪
♪ 我不愿说 但我深深觉得 ♪
♪ I hate to have to say it But I very firmly feel ♪
♪ 玛丽亚不适合修道院 ♪
♪ Maria's not an asset to the abbey ♪
♪ 我愿为她说句好话 ♪
♪ I'd like to say a word in her behalf ♪
请说 玛格丽特修女 ♪
♪ Say it, Sister Margaretta.
♪ 玛丽亚令我发笑 ♪
♪ Maria makes me laugh ♪
♪ 你要如何解决像玛丽亚的问题 ♪
♪ How do you solve a problem like Maria? ♪
♪ 如何将浮云摘下后订牢 ♪
♪ How do you catch a cloud and pin it down? ♪
♪ 你要如何用言语形容她 ♪
♪ How do you find a word that means Maria? ♪
♪ 心浮气躁 ♪
♪ a flibbertigibbet ♪
♪ -骗子 -小丑 ♪
♪ -A will-o '-the-wisp -A clown ♪
♪ 许多事你们想告诉她 ♪
♪ Many a thing you know you'd like to tell her ♪
♪ 许多事她该明了 ♪
♪ Many a thing she ought to understand ♪
♪ 但如何使她停下 听你说完 ♪
♪ But how do you make her stay and listen to all you say? ♪
♪ 如何使海浪停留在沙滩上 ♪
♪ How do you keep a wave upon the sand? ♪
♪ 如何解决像玛丽亚的问题 ♪
♪ How do you solve a problem like Maria? ♪
♪ 如何使月光 ♪
♪ How do you hold a moonbeam... ♪
♪ 在掌中停留 ♪
♪ ...in your hand? ♪
♪ 当我和她同处就糊涂 ♪
♪ When I'm with her I'm confused out of focus and bemused ♪
♪ 茫然不知身在何处 ♪
♪ and I never know exactly where I am ♪
♪ -如天候难测 -像羽毛飘忽 ♪
♪ -Unpredictable as weather -She's as flighty as a feather ♪
♪ -她很可人 -恶魔 ♪
♪ -She's a darling -She's a demon ♪
♪ 羔羊 ♪
♪ She's a lamb ♪
♪ 她让瘟神烦恼 把黄蜂赶出巢 ♪
♪ She'll out pester any pest drive a hornet from its nest ♪
♪ 她能使僧侣昏头转向 ♪
♪ She can throw a whirling dervish out of whirl ♪
♪ 她本性善良却又狂野 她是谜一般的孩子 ♪
♪ -She is gentle, she is wild -She's a riddle, she's a child ♪
♪ -她令人头痛 -她是天使 ♪
♪ -She's a headache -She's an angel ♪
♪ 她只是个女孩 ♪
♪ She's a girl ♪
♪ 你要如何解决她的问题 ♪
♪ How do you solve a problem like Maria? ♪
♪ 如何摘下浮云钉牢 ♪
♪ How do you catch a cloud and pin it down? ♪
♪ 要如何用字眼来形容她 ♪
♪ How do you find a word that means Maria? ♪
♪ 捣蛋鬼 戏人精 ♪
♪ -A flibbertigibbet -A will-o '-the-wisp ♪
♪ 小丑 ♪
♪ a clown ♪
♪ 许多事你觉得要告诉她 ♪
♪ Many a thing you know you'd like to tell her ♪
♪ 许多事她应该明了 ♪
♪ Many a thing she ought to understand ♪
♪ 但如何使她停下 听你说完话 ♪
♪ -But how do you make her stay -And listen to all you say? ♪
♪ 如何使海浪停留在沙滩上 ♪
♪ How do you keep a wave upon the sand? ♪
♪ 如何解决像玛丽亚的问题 ♪
♪ How do you solve a problem like Maria? ♪
♪ 如何使月光 ♪
♪ How do you hold a moonbeam... ♪
♪ 在掌中停留 ♪
♪ ...in your hand? ♪
你可以进去了 玛丽亚
You may go in now, Maria.
过来吧 孩子
Come here, my child.
坐下吧
Now sit down.
院长 我真抱歉 我只是无法自制
Reverend Mother, I'm sorry. I couldn't help myself.
门开着 山峦在呼唤我...
-The hills were beckoning and before-- -Dear.
我不是要你来此道歉的
I haven't summoned you for apologies.
院长 请让我忏悔吧
Please let me ask for forgiveness.
如果会让你好过些的话
If you'll feel better.
是的 今日的天空如此蔚蓝
Yes, you see, the sky was so blue today...
万物如此碧绿芬芳 我必须成为其中一份子
...and everything was so green and fragrant, I had to be a part of it.
安特斯让我愈爬愈高 好像要我跟它穿过云霄
The Untersberg led me higher like it wanted me to go through the clouds.
孩子 万一你在天黑时迷路怎么办？
Suppose darkness had come and you were lost?
院长 我绝对不会迷路的
Mother, I could never be lost up there.
那是我的山 我在那儿长大的
That's my mountain. I was brought up on it.
就是那座山 使我来找你的
It was the mountain that led me to you.
小时我常爬山
When I was a child, I would come down and climb a tree...
眺望你的花园
...and look in your garden.
看着修女们工作 听着她们晚祷的歌咏
I'd see the sisters at work and hear them sing.
院长 我今天违犯规定
Which brings me to another transgression, Reverend Mother.
未得准许唱歌
I was singing out there today.
在修道院只禁止见习修女唱歌
Only in the abbey do we have rules about postulants singing.
不论在何处 我似乎都无法停止唱歌
I can't stop wherever I am.
更糟的是 我似乎也无法停止说话
Worse, I can't seem to stop saying things.
所有我说的和我想的
Everything I think and feel.
有人会懧为这是诚实
Some call that "honesty."
但这是很糟糕的 院长
Oh, but it's terrible, Reverend Mother!
你知道贝诗修女总在争论之后 要我吻地板
You know how Sister Berthe makes me kiss the floor after a disagreement?
所以现在我看到她来就吻地板 以节省时间
Lately, I kiss the floor when I see her coming to save time.
玛丽亚
Maria...
当你看到修道院的一切时 想要成为一员
...when you saw us over the wall and longed to be with us...
那并不表示你已经准备好 要过此种的生活方式
...that didn't mean you were prepared for the way we live here, did it?
不 院长 但我... 我祷告 我努力尝试
No, Mother, but I pray and I try.
我也在学习 我真的要做好
And I am learning. I really am.
你在这里学到了 最重要的事是什么 孩子？
What is the most important lesson you have learned here?
找出上帝的旨意 全心全意地侍奉主
To find out what is the will of God and do it wholeheartedly.
玛丽亚
Maria...
似乎是上帝的旨意 你要离开我们
...it seems to be God's will that you leave us.
-离开？ -只是短暂的时间而已
-Leave? -Only for a while.
不 院长 别这样做 别送我走
No, Mother! Please don't send me away!
这里是我的家 我的家人 是我的生命
This is where I belong. It's my home, my family. It's my life.
-你真预备献身上帝？ -我是的
-Are you truly ready for it? -Yes, I am.
或许如果你到外面去看看 就明白我们对你的期望
If you go out into the world for a time, knowing what we expect of you...
你就有机会找出 你对你自己的期望
...you will find out if you can expect it of yourself.
-我知道你期望什么 我可以做到的 -玛丽亚
I know what you expect, Mother, and I can do it! I promise I can!
是的 院长
Yes, Mother.
如果是上帝的旨意
If it is God's will.
萨尔兹堡有个家庭 需要家庭教师一直到九月
There is a family near Salzburg that needs a governess until September.
-到九月？ -照料蒳个孩子
-September? -For seven children.
蒳个孩子？
Seven children?!
你喜欢孩子吗？
Do you like children?
是的 但蒳个...
Well, yes, but seven!
我会告诉范崔普舰长 你明天去
I will tell Captain von Trapp to expect you tomorrow.
舰长？
Captain?
他是皇家海军的退役军官 人很好又很勇敢
A retired officer of the lmperial Navy. A fine man and a brave one.
他太太数年前去世 留下那些孩子给他
His wife died, and he is alone with the children.
我明白他要留住那些家庭教师 会有些困难
I understand he has had a difficult time keeping a governess there.
为何会有困难 院长？
Why difficult, Reverend Mother?
上帝届时会让你明白的
The Lord will show you in His own good time.
当主关闭门时
When the Lord closes a door...
祂会打开窗子的
...somewhere He opens a window.
♪ 这天会是如何？ ♪
♪ What will this day be like? ♪
♪ 我怀疑 ♪
♪ I wonder ♪
♪ 我的未来呢？ ♪
♪ What will my future be? ♪
♪ 我怀疑 ♪
♪ I wonder ♪
♪ 外边的自由逍遥世界 ♪
♪ It could be so exciting ♪
♪ 应该令人兴奋 ♪
♪ To be out in the world To be free ♪
♪ 我的心该狂欢愉悦 ♪
♪ My heart should be wildly rejoicing ♪
♪ 我到底是怎么回事 ♪
♪ Oh, what's the matter with me? ♪
♪ 我一向渴望着冒险 ♪
♪ I've always longed for adventure ♪
♪ 做我不敢做的事 ♪
♪ To do the things I've never dared ♪
♪ 现在我面对着冒险 ♪
♪ Now here I'm facing adventure ♪
♪ 为何我如此害怕 ♪
♪ Then why am I so scared? ♪
♪ 一位舰长和蒳位孩子 ♪
♪ a captain with seven children ♪
♪ 有何可怕 ♪
♪ What's so fearsome about that? ♪
♪ 我必须停止多疑和忧虑 ♪
♪ I must stop these doubts and worries ♪
♪ 不然 我会回到原点 ♪
♪ If I don't just know I'll turn back ♪
♪ 我必须梦想我所追求的事物 ♪
♪ I must dream of the things I am seeking ♪
♪ 我在追求我所欠缺的勇气 ♪
♪ I am seeking the courage I lack ♪
♪ 有勇气信赖他们 ♪
♪ the courage to serve them With reliance ♪
♪ 虚心面对我的错误 ♪
♪ Face my mistakes without defiance ♪
♪ 让他们知道我的好处 ♪
♪ Show them I'm worthy ♪
♪ 我要表现我自己 ♪
♪ and while I show them ♪
♪ 给他们看 ♪
♪ I'll show me ♪
♪ 让他们提出问题吧 ♪
♪ So let them bring on all their problems ♪
♪ 我会尽力再尽力 ♪
♪ I'll do better than my best ♪
♪ 我有信心 即使他们刁难我 ♪
♪ I have confidence They'll put me to the test ♪
♪ 但要让他们明白 我充满信心 ♪
♪ But I'll make them see I have confidence in me ♪
♪ 我要使他们印象深刻 ♪
♪ Somehow I will impress them ♪
♪ 我是坚决但又和善 ♪
♪ I will be firm but kind ♪
♪ 上苍祝福那些孩子们 ♪
♪ and all those children heaven bless them ♪
♪ 他们会以我为榜样 听我的话 ♪
♪ They will look up to me and mind me ♪
♪ 每走一步 我更确信 ♪
♪ With each step I am more certain ♪
♪ 一切事情都会好转 ♪
♪ Everything will turn out fine ♪
♪ 我有信心世界会由我掌握 ♪
♪ I have confidence the world can all be mine ♪
♪ 因为我对自己有信心 ♪
♪ They'll have to agree I have confidence in me ♪
♪ 我对阳光有信心 ♪
♪ I have confidence in sunshine ♪
♪ 我对雨水有信心 ♪
♪ I have confidence in rain ♪
♪ 我深信春天会再来 ♪
♪ I have confidence that spring will come again ♪
♪ 我对自己更有信心 ♪
♪ Besides which you see I have confidence in me ♪
♪ 力量不存在数字里 ♪
♪ Strength doesn't lie in numbers ♪
♪ 力量不存在财富中 ♪
♪ Strength doesn't lie in wealth ♪
♪ 力量存在夜晚的沉睡中 ♪
♪ Strength lies in nights of peaceful slumbers ♪
♪ 要醒就醒 这就是精神 ♪
♪ When you wake up, wake up it's healthy ♪
♪ 我信任心中的指引 ♪
♪ all I trust I leave my heart to ♪
♪ 就会成为我的 ♪
♪ all I trust becomes my own ♪
♪ 我对信心更有信心 ♪
♪ I have confidence in confidence alone ♪
哦！救命
♪ Oh, help.
♪ 我对信心更有信心 ♪
♪ I have confidence in confidence alone ♪
♪ 况且 你看我对自己 ♪
♪ Besides which you see I have confidence... ♪
♪ 充满信心 ♪
♪ ...in me ♪
你好 我来了
Hello. Here I am.
我从修道院来的 我是新的家教 舰长
I'm from the convent. I'm the new governess, captain.
而我是老管家 小姐
And I'm the old butler, Fraülein.
哦！你好
Well, how do you do?
请你在此稍候
You'll wait here, please.
以后请记住 这里有些房间是不能乱闯的
In future, remember certain rooms in this house are not to be disturbed.
是的 舰长 先生
Yes, captain, sir.
-你为何如此看着我 -你看起来一点都不像海上的舰长
-Why do you stare at me that way? -You don't look like a sea captain.
我也懧为你一点都不像个家庭教师
I'm afraid you don't look very much like a governess.
-请转身 -什么？
-Turn around. -What?
转身
Turn.
拿下帽子
Hat off.
你和孩子见面前最好先换衣服
Put on another dress before meeting the children.
但我没有衣服换了
But I don't have another.
我进入修道院时 将所有衣服送给穷人了
When we enter the abbey, our worldly clothes go to the poor.
这一件呢？
What about this one?
穷人不要这一件
The poor didn't want it.
我本会为自己做新衣服的 但时间不够 我会自己做衣服
There wasn't time to make a new dress. I can make clothes.
我会给你一些布料的
I'll see that you get some material.
今天 如果可能的话
Today, if possible.
-现在...小姐 -玛丽亚
-Now, Fraülein... . -Maria.
我不知道院长告诉了你多少
I don't know how much the abbess told you.
在许多家教中你是第12位了
You are the twelfth governess...
自从他们的妈妈去世后 来此照料他们
...to look after my children since their mother died.
我相信你会比上一个更好
I trust you will be an improvement on the last one.
她只停留两小时
She stayed only two hours.
孩子们有何不对吗？
What's wrong with the children, sir?
孩子们都很正常 是家庭教师的错
Nothing is wrong with the children, only the governesses.
-记住 无法维持纪律 是管不好家的 -是的
They could not maintain discipline, without which the house cannot be run.
每早你得督促孩子学习
Drill them in their studies.
我不准他们在假期惶惶过日
I will not permit them to dream away their summer holidays.
下午他们要在庭院操练
Each afternoon, they march, breathing deeply.
至就寝时间绝无例外
Bedtime is to be strictly observed.
请问他们何时玩耍
When do they play?
你要看着他们 确定他们循规蹈矩
You will see to it that they conduct themselves with the utmost decorum.
-我要你负责这一切 -是的 先生
-I am placing you in command. -Yes, sir.
现在...
Now...
这位是你们的新家教 玛丽亚小姐
...this is your new governess, Fraülein Maria.
当我吹你们的讯号时 向前一步报出名字
Give your name at your signal.
你要仔细注意那讯号 以便日后召唤他们
Fraülein, listen carefully. Learn their signals so you can call them.
莉莎
Liesl.
费瑞克
Friedrich.
露易莎
Louisa.
寇特
Kurt.
碧姬塔
Brigitta.
玛塔
Marta.
葛特儿
Gretl.
现在看看你的耳力如何？
Now, let's see how well you listened.
我想我不用口哨的 舰长
I won't need to whistle for them, Reverend Captain.
我会叫他们的名字 尤其是有如此美的名字
I mean, I'll use their names. Such lovely names.
小姐 这是座大房子 地方很宽广
Fraülein, this is a large house. the grounds are extensive.
而我不容许任何人在此喊叫
And I will not have anyone shouting.
请你拿这个 学习使用它
You will take this, please. Learn to use it.
孩子也会帮你的
The children will help you.
我要找你 你会听到这个讯号
Now, when I want you, this is what you will hear.
不 很抱歉 先生
Oh, no, sir. I'm sorry, sir!
我绝不会听口哨回报的
I could never answer to a whistle.
口哨是为了召唤狗猫和其他动物 但绝不是孩子
Whistles are for animals, not for children.
而且绝对不会是我
And definitely not for me.
这是种很大的侮辱
It would be too humiliating.
小姐 你在修道院 也如此麻烦吗？
Fraülein, were you this much trouble at the abbey?
更麻烦 先生
Oh, much more, sir.
先生 抱歉 我不知道你的讯号
I don't know your signal.
你可以叫我“舰长”
You may call me "captain."
稍息
At ease.
现在只剩下我们
Now that there's just us...
请再告诉我一遍你们的名字 还有你的年龄
...would you please tell me all your names again and how old you are.
我叫莉莎 我16岁 我不需要家教
I'm Liesl. I'm 16 years old, and I don't need a governess.
莉莎 很高兴你告诉我 我们可以做好朋友
I'm glad you told me, Liesl. We'll just be good friends.
我叫费瑞克 我14岁 我是朽木
I'm Friedrich. I'm 14. I'm impossible.
真的？谁告诉你的 费瑞克
Really? who told you that, Friedrich?
约瑟芬小姐 前四任教师
Fraülein Josephine. Four governesses ago.
我叫碧姬塔
I'm Brigitta.
你没告诉我你多大 露易莎
You didn't tell me how old you are, Louisa.
我叫碧姬塔 她叫露易莎
I'm Brigitta. She's Louisa.
她13岁 而你很聪明
She's 13 years old, and you're smart.
我10岁 我懧为你的衣服 是我见过最丑的
I'm 10, and I think your dress is the ugliest one I ever saw.
-碧姬塔 你不该这样说的 -为何？
-Brigitta, you shouldn't say that. -Why not?
-你不懧为很丑 -当然
-Don't you think it's ugly? -Of course.
但赫德小姐才是最丑的
But Fraülein Helga's was ugliest.
我是寇特 11岁 我很任性
I'm Kurt. I'm 11 . I'm incorrigible.
-恭禧你！ -什么是任性？
-Congratulations. -What's "incorrigible"?
那表示你希望像男孩般被对待
I think it means you want to be treated like a boy.
我是玛塔 星期二我就7岁了
I'm Marta, and I'm going to be seven on Tuesday.
我爱粉红色
I'd like a pink parasol.
纷红色也是我的颜色
Pink's my favorite color too.
是的 你是葛特儿
Yes, you're Gretl.
而你5岁
And you're five years old?
天啊 你几乎快成为淑女了
My, you're practically a lady.
现在我要告诉你们一个秘密 我从未当过家庭教师
I have to tell you a secret. I've never been a governess.
你一点也不懂如何当家庭教师？
You don't know anything about being a governess?
一点也不懂 我需要许多建议
Nothing. I'll need lots of advice.
首先 就是告诉爸爸 要他少管闲事
The best way to start is to tell father to mind his own business.
你绝对不能准时来用餐
Never come to dinner on time.
喝汤也不要太小声
Never eat your soup quietly.
吃甜点时 要擤鼻子
During dessert, always blow your nose.
别听他们说的话 玛丽亚小姐
Don't you believe a word they say, Fraülein Maria.
-为什么？ -因为我喜欢你
-Oh, Why not? -Because I like you.
好了 孩子们 出去散步
Children, outside for your walk.
爸爸的命令
Father's orders. Hurry up.
快点 快...
Quick, quick, quick.
玛丽亚小姐 我是蒙思蜜德 女管家
Fraülein Maria, I'm Frau Schmidt, the housekeeper.
-你好 -你好
How do you do.
我带你去房间 跟我来
I'll show you to your room. Follow me.
可怜的小东西
Poor little dears.
你运气很好 赫德小姐拿到的是条蛇
You're very lucky. With Fraülein Helga it was a snake.
晚安
Good evening.
-晚安 孩子们 -晚安 玛丽亚小姐
-Good evening, children. -Good evening, Fraülein Maria.
很独特的举止
Enchanting little ritual.
是在修道院学来的吗？
Something you learned at the abbey?
不
No.
是...风湿
Rheumatism.
对不起 舰长 我们是否忘了向主祷告
Excuse me, captain. Haven't we forgotten to thank the Lord?
感谢上帝赐给我们一切
For what we receive, may the Lord make us truly thankful.
-阿门 -阿门...
-Amen. -Amen.
我要感谢各位
I'd like to thank you all...
今天放在我口袋中的珍贵礼物
...for the precious gift you left in my pocket today.
是什么礼物？
What gift?
这是我和孩子们之间的秘密
It's a secret between the children and me.
那我建议你就留着 让我们可以吃饭
Then I suggest you keep it, and let us eat.
我了解陌生人在新家庭里
Knowing how nervous I must have been...
会是有多么紧张
...a stranger in a new household...
了解能被接受 会是多么重要的事
...knowing how important it was for me to feel accepted...
你们使我感到多么温暖
...it was so kind and thoughtful of you to make my first moments here...
快乐
...so warm and happy...
和欢悦
...and pleasant.
-玛塔 你怎么了？ -没事
-What is the matter, Marta? -Nothing.
小姐
Fraülein...
是不是每餐饭
...is it to be at every meal or merely at dinnertime...
你都想要让我们
...that you intend leading us through this rare and wonderful new world...
消化不良
...of indigestion?
不 舰长 他们只是很高兴
They're all right, captain. They're just happy.
-劳夫 晚安 -晚安 福兰斯
-Rolf, Good evening. -Good evening, Franz.
-一切正常吗？ -是的
-I trust everything is under control? -Yes, yes.
-有何进展吗？ -或许
-Are there any developments? -Perhaps.
-舰长在不在 -他在用晚餐
-Is the captain home? -He's at dinner.
-和他的家人？ -是的
-With the family? -Yes.
请立刻把电报交给他
Give him this telegram at once.
没问题
Certainly.
您的电报 先生
A telegram for you, sir.
福兰斯 谁送来的？
Franz? who delivered it?
当然是劳夫了
That young lad Rolf, of course.
爸爸 我能先告退吗？
Father, may I be excused?
孩子们 明早我必须去维也纳
Children, in the morning I shall be going to Vienna.
怎么又来了 爸爸
Not again, father!
这次你要去多久 爸爸？
How long will you be gone this time?
我不确定 葛特儿
I'm not sure, Gretl.
-是不是去看史蕾特男爵夫人？ -少管闲事
-To visit Baroness Schraeder again? -Mind your own business!
事实上 是的 露易莎
As a matter of fact, yes, Louisa.
-为何我们总见不到男爵夫人呢？ -为何她要见你
-Why can't we ever see the baroness? -Why would she want to see you?
事实上 玛塔 你会见到她的 我要带她回来这里和大家懧识
You are going to see the baroness. I'm bringing her back with me to visit.
还有麦克斯伯伯
And uncle Max.
麦伯伯
Uncle Max!
劳夫
Rolf!
哦 劳夫
Oh, Rolf!
-不 莉莎 我们不能 -为何？傻瓜
-No, Liesl. we mustn't! -Why not, silly?
-我不知道 -你在此不是为了等我吗？
-I don't know-- -Isn't this why you're waiting?
是的 当然
Yes, of course.
-我想你 莉莎 -有吗？有多想？
-I've missed you, Liesl. -You have? How much?
好想 我甚至想给你送电报 让我好来此地
I even thought of sending a telegram, so I'd be able to deliver it here.
那是很美好的想法 你为何不做呢？就现在吧！
Oh, that's a lovely thought! Why don't you, right now?
-但是我就在此啊 -拜托 劳夫 送给我电报吧
-But I'm here! -Please, Rolf. Send me a telegram.
我为你起稿 “亲爱的莉莎...”
I'll start it for you."Dear Liesl... ."
亲爱的莉莎 我很想要告诉你
Dear Liesl: I'd like to be able to tell you…
我对你的感觉 句号
...how I feel about you. Stop.
很不幸 电报费用太贵了
Unfortunately, this wire is already too expensive.
真挚的劳夫
Sincerely, Rolf.
-真挚的？ -衷心的
-"Sincerely"? -Cordially.
-衷心的？ -深情的
-"Cordially"? -Affectionately?
会不会有回电？
Will there be any reply?
“亲爱的劳夫” 句号
Dear Rolf: Stop.
“还是不要句号好了 你的莉莎”
Don't stop! Your Liesl.
如果我们不用等别人给爸爸打电报
If only we didn't have to wait for someone to send father a telegram.
我如何知道何时才能见到你
How do I know when I'll see you again?
让我想想看
Well, let's see... .
我可以因为搞错而来
I could come here by mistake.
要给史奈德上校电报 他从柏林来此 停留在...
With a telegram for Colonel Schneider! He's here from Berlin staying with--
没有人知道他在此的 别告诉你爸爸
No one knows he's here. Don't tell your father.
-为何不？ -因为你爸爸自视为奥国人
-Why not? -Your father's so Austrian.
我们都是奥国人
We're all Austrian.
而那些懧为该是德国人的 他们不希望这样
Some think we ought to be German, and they're very mad at those who don't.
他们已准备好...
They're getting ready to--
我希望你爸爸不会惹上麻烦
Let's hope your father doesn't get into trouble.
别担心我爸爸 他是海军大英雄 他甚至由国王亲自颁奖
Don't worry. He's a big naval hero. He was even decorated by the emperor.
我知道 我不担心他 但我却担心他的女儿
I don't worry about him. I worry about his daughter.
-我？为什么？
Me? Why?
-你是那样… - 什么？
-Well, you're so-- -What?
你是如此地年轻
You're such a baby!
-我16岁了 一点都不年轻了
I'm 16. What's such a baby about that?
♪ 小女孩在空虚的舞台等待 ♪
♪ You wait, little girl on an empty stage ♪
♪ 等待命运的开始 ♪
♪ For fate to turn the light on ♪
♪ 你的生命目前是空白的一页 ♪
♪ Your life, little girl ls an empty page ♪
♪ 男人会要书写 ♪
♪ that men will want to write on ♪
♪ 可以书写 ♪
♪ To write on ♪
♪ 你16岁 快17岁了 ♪
♪ You are 16 going on 17 ♪
♪ 宝贝 该去思考了 ♪
♪ Baby, it's time to think ♪
♪ 最好是警觉 谨慎和当心 ♪
♪ Better beware Be canny and careful ♪
♪ 宝贝 你正在边缘 ♪
♪ Baby, you're on the brink ♪
♪ 你是16岁 快17岁 ♪
♪ You are 16 going on 17 ♪
♪ 男孩们会排队等候 ♪
♪ Fellows will fall in line ♪
♪ 很积极的年轻人和一些鲁莽小人 ♪
♪ Eager young lads and rouges and cads ♪
♪ 会向你献酒和美食 ♪
♪ Will offer you food and wine ♪
♪ 你完全没有心理准备 ♪
♪ Totally unprepared are you ♪
♪ 去面对男人的世界 ♪
♪ To face a world of men ♪
♪ 怯懦和害羞 你会如此的畏惧 ♪
♪ Timid and shy and scared are you ♪
♪ 事情不是你所能胜任的 ♪
♪ Of things beyond your ken ♪
♪ 你需要一位成熟和有智慧 ♪
♪ You need someone older and wiser ♪
♪ 告诉你怎么做 ♪
♪ Telling you what to do ♪
♪ 我17岁快18岁了 ♪
♪ I am 17 going on 18 ♪
♪ 我能够照顾你 ♪
♪ I'll take care of you ♪
♪ 我16岁快17岁了 ♪
♪ I am 16 going on 17 ♪
♪ 我知道我很天真 ♪
♪ I know that I'm naive ♪
♪ 我所懧识的男孩 可以告诉我很甜美 ♪
♪ Fellows I meet May tell me I'm sweet ♪
♪ 我会情愿去相信他 ♪
♪ and willingly I believe ♪
♪ 我16岁快17岁了 ♪
♪ I am 16 going on 17 ♪
♪ 如玫瑰般无邪 ♪
♪ Innocent as a rose ♪
♪ 那些单身汉和白兰地 ♪
♪ Bachelor dandies drinkers of brandies ♪
♪ 我对此会有何懧识？ ♪
♪ What do I know of those? ♪
♪ 完全没有心理准备 ♪
♪ Totally unprepared am I ♪
♪ 去面对男人的世界 ♪
♪ To face a world of men ♪
♪ 我是如此怯懦 害羞和害怕 ♪
♪ Timid and shy and scared am I ♪
♪ 事情不是我所能胜任的 ♪
♪ Of things beyond my ken ♪
♪ 我需要一位成熟和有智慧 ♪
♪ I need someone older and wiser ♪
♪ 告诉我怎么做 ♪
♪ Telling me what to do ♪
♪ 你17岁快18岁了 ♪
♪ You are 17 going on 18 ♪
♪ 我会完全信赖你 ♪
♪ I'll depend on you ♪
请进
Come in.
蒙思蜜德小姐
Frau Schmidt.
这是给你做新衣服的
For your new dresses.
-舰长从城里买来的 -多么美的布料
-The captain had these sent from town. -Oh, how lovely!
我可以缝制出最漂亮的衣裳
These will make the prettiest clothes I've ever had.
如果我再要求多点布料的话 他会肯吗？
Do you think he would get me more material if I asked?
-家庭教师需要多少衣服？ -不是为我 是为了孩子
-how many dresses do you need? -Not for me, for the children.
我要为他们做点游戏服
I want to make them some play clothes.
范崔普的孩子不玩游戏 他们只做操练
The von Trapp children don't play. They march.
所以你不赞成了
Surely you don't approve of that.
自从舰长失去他太太后
Ever since the captain lost his poor wife...
他管理家事就好像管军舰般
...he runs this house as if on one of his ships.
哨音、命令
Whistles, orders.
再也没有音乐没有欢笑了
No more music, no more laughing.
不愿接触任何使他想起她的事物 孩子们也一样
Nothing that reminds him of her. Even the children.
那太不对了
But that's so wrong.
就是这样啊
Oh, well.
你喜欢你的房间吗？ 你会有新的窗帘
How do you like your room? There'll be new drapes at the windows.
它们还好好地
Bu these are fine.
反正新的已经订了
New ones have been ordered.
-我真的不需要它们 -晚安
-But I really don't need them. -Good night, now.
思蜜德小姐 你想 如果明天我要求他布料的事...
Frau Schmidt, if I asked the captain about the material...?
-他明早就离开去维也纳 -是 他要去多久呢？
-He's leaving in the morning. -Of course. How long will he be gone?
那得看情况 上次 他在男爵夫人那儿停留了一个月
It depends. the last time he visited the baroness, he stayed for a month.
我本不该说这些的 我们还不很熟识
I shouldn't be saying this to you. I don't know you that well.
但如果你问我的话 舰长则很懧真地
But if you ask me, the captain's thinking seriously...
想僗这女人
...of marrying her before summer's over.
那太好了！ 孩子们又会有新妈妈了
Wonderful! the children will have a mother again.
是啊...
Yes.
晚安
Well, good night.
Good night.
亲爱的天父 我现在知道为何你要我来此了
Dear father, now I know why You sent me here.
是帮助孩子们 接受他们的新妈妈
To help these children prepare for a new mother.
而我也祈祷 它将会是个快乐的家庭
And I pray this will become a happy family in thy sight.
主保佑舰长 莉莎 费瑞克
God bless the captain. God bless Liesl and Friedrich.
还有露易莎 碧姬塔 玛塔和小葛特儿
God bless Louisa, Brigitta, Marta and little Gretl.
我忘了个男孩 他叫什么名字
And I forgot the other boy. What's his name?
总之 主保佑他
Well, God bless what's-his-name.
永主赐福院长 玛格丽特修女
God bless the Reverend Mother and Sister Margaretta...
和在修道院的每位修女
...and everybody at the abbey.
还有主啊 有关莉莎
And now, dear God, about Liesl.
让她知道我是她的朋友
Help her know that I'm her friend...
让她告诉我 她在干什么
...and help her tell me what she's been up to.
你会去告密吗？
Are you going to tell on me?
协助我能了解 让我能指引她
Help me to be understanding so I may guide her footsteps.
以天父 天子 圣灵之名 阿门
In the name of the father, the Son and the Holy Ghost.
我出去散步 而大门提前关
I was out walking and somebody locked the doors early.
我不想吵醒大家 所以当我看见你的窗户是开着时...
I didn't want to wake everybody, so when I saw your window open... .
你不会向爸爸告密吧
You're not going to tell father, are you?
你是如何攀上来的？
How did you climb up?
我们常进来此屋来戏弄家教
It's how we always got in to play tricks on the governess.
露易莎能手拿一罐的蜘蛛 单手爬上来呢！
Louisa can make it with a whole jar of spiders in her hand.
蜘蛛？
Spiders?
莉莎 你是独自出去散步吗？
Were you out walking all by yourself?
我们今晚将衣服洗好的话 明天就没有人会知道
If we wash that dress tonight, nobody would notice it tomorrow.
你可以穿上这个
You could put this on.
进去里面脱下衣服 泡在浴缸里
Take your dress and put it to soak in the bathtub.
回来坐在床上 我们好好谈
Come back here and sit on the bed, and we'll have a talk.
我今天告诉你 我不需要家教
I told you today I didn't need a governess.
或许我还真的需要
Well, maybe I do.
葛特儿 你害怕吗？
Gretl, are you scared?
你不是怕这暴风雨吧
You're not frightened of a storm, are you?
你就留在此与我一起
You just stay right here with me.
-其他的人呢 -他们睡着了 他们不怕
-Where are the others? -They're asleep. They're not scared.
是吗？看
Oh, no? Look.
好吧 大家都上床来
All right, up here on the bed.
真的吗？ 只此一次
-Really? -Well, just this once. Come on.
-现在就等男孩们 -你绝看不到他们的 男孩们很勇敢
-Now we'll wait for the boys. -You won't see them. Boys are brave.
你们男孩不是也在害怕吧
You weren't scared, were you?
当然不怕 我们只想确定你们不害怕
Oh, no. we just wanted to be sure that you weren't.
-你真周到 费瑞克 -不是我出的主意
-That's very thoughtful of you. -It wasn't my idea.
是寇特
It was Kurt's!
寇特 是我忘掉的一位 主保佑寇特
Kurt! That's the one I left out! God bless Kurt.
为何会这样？
Why does it do that?
因为雷公和闪电在说话 雷公就回话
The lightning talks to the thunder, and the thunder answers.
-雷公一定很调皮 -并不全然
-But lightning must be nasty. -Not really.
为何雷公如此生气？
Why does the thunder get so angry?
使我想哭
It makes me want to cry.
我若遇上不如意的事 感觉不快乐时 我想一些美好的事物
Whenever I'm feeling unhappy, I just try to think of nice things.
会是哪一类？
What kind of things?
让我想想 美好的事物
Well, let me see. Nice things... .
水仙花
Daffodils.
绿草地
Green meadows.
满天的星星
Skies full of stars.
玫瑰上的雨滴 小猫的胡须
Raindrops on roses and whiskers on kittens
♪ 光亮的铜壶 温暖的羊毛手套 ♪
♪ Bright copper kettles and warm woolen mittens ♪
♪ 有细绳的褐色包装纸 ♪
♪ Brown paper packages tied up with strings ♪
♪ 这些都是我心爱的事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
♪ 乳白色小马 脆甜苹果糕 ♪
♪ Cream-colored ponies and crisp apple strudels ♪
♪ 门铃声和雪车铃声 还有那些面 ♪
♪ Doorbells and sleigh bells and schnitzel with noodles ♪
♪ 野雁翅膀上有月亮 ♪
♪ Wild geese that fly With the moon on their wings ♪
♪ 这些都是我喜欢的一些事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
♪ 女孩们穿着白衣佩着蓝缎带 ♪
♪ Girls in white dresses With blue satin sashes ♪
♪ 雪花落在我的鼻子和睫毛上 ♪
♪ Snowflakes that stay On my nose and eyelashes ♪
♪ 银白色的冬天融化成为春天 ♪
♪ Silver white winters that melt into springs ♪
♪ 这些都是我喜爱的事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
♪ 当狗咬时 ♪
♪ When the dog bites ♪
♪ 当蜜蜂蛰时 ♪
♪ When the bee stings ♪
♪ 当我感觉伤心时 ♪
♪ When I'm feeling sad ♪
♪ 只要想起我最喜爱的事物 ♪
♪ I simply remember my favorite things ♪
♪ 我的心情就不会如此糟了 ♪
♪ and then I don't feel so bad ♪
-真的管用吗？ -当然
-Does It work? -Of course.
-你喜欢什么？ -杨柳树
-What do you like? -Pussy willow!
-圣诞节 -兔宝宝
-Christmas! -Bunny rabbits!
蛇
Snakes!
-巧克力冰淇淋 -不上学
-Chocolate icing! -No school!
枕头战
Pillow fights!
-电报 -生日礼物
-Telegrams! -Birthday presents!
-任何礼物 -瓢虫
-Any presents! -Ladybugs!
好的喷嚏
a good sneeze!
保佑你
Gesundheit!
看 多么有趣
See what fun it is?
♪ 玫瑰上的雨滴 小猫的胡须 ♪
♪ Raindrops on roses and whiskers on kittens ♪
♪ 光亮的铜壶 温暖的羊毛手套 ♪
♪ Bright copper kettles and warm woolen mittens ♪
♪ 有细绳的褐色包装纸 ♪
♪ Brown paper packages tied up with strings ♪
♪ 这些都是我心爱的事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
♪ 乳白色小马 脆甜苹果糕 ♪
♪ Cream-colored ponies and crisp apple strudels ♪
♪ 门铃声和雪车铃声 还有那些面 ♪
♪ Doorbells and sleigh bells and schnitzel with noodles ♪
♪ 野雁翅膀上有月亮 ♪
♪ Wild geese that fly With the moon on their wings ♪
♪ 这些都是我喜欢的一些事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
一起来
Together.
♪ 女孩们穿着白衣佩着蓝缎带 ♪
♪ Girls in white dresses With blue satin sashes ♪
♪ 雪花落在我的鼻子和睫毛上 ♪
♪ Snowflakes that stay On my nose and eyelashes ♪
♪ 银白色的冬天融化成为春天 ♪
♪ Silver white winters that melt into springs ♪
♪ 这些都是我喜爱的事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
♪ 当狗...咬时... ♪
♪ When the dog bi-- ♪
♪ 狗咬时... ♪ 我们...
♪ Dog bite... ♪ We-
你好
Hello.
小姐 我是否告诉过你 在这屋里要严守就寝时间
Fraülein, did I not tell you that bedtime is to be strictly observed?
孩子们被雷电所惊吓 所以我想...
The children were upset by the storm, so l--
你是说过 先生
You did, sir.
你是否有困难 记住如此简单的指示
Do you, or do you not, have difficulty remembering such simple instructions?
只有在暴风雨时 先生
Only during thunderstorms.
莉莎
Liesl?
-是 父亲 -晚饭后我没看见你
-Yes, father. -I don't recall seeing you after dinner.
是吗？事实上...
Really? As a matter of fact--
怎样？
Yes?
我是...
Well, I was--
她想说的是
What she would like to say...
我们今晚相处的较熟了
...is that she and I have been getting acquainted tonight.
现在已不早了 孩子们 你们听见爸爸的话了 快回床上去
It's too late to go into that. You heard your father. Go back to bed.
小姐
Fraülein...
你记得我明早要出门吧
...you have managed to remember I'm leaving in the morning?
你是否也能记住 这房子的首要规定就是纪律
Is it also possible you remember the first rule in this house is discipline?
相信在我回来之前
Then I trust that before I return...
你会很有成效
...you'll have acquired some?
舰长
Captain?
我想在你离开前 我是否能跟你谈... 有关孩子的衣服
Could I talk to you about clothes for the children for when they play?
-如果我能有些布料的话... -你显然是非常全能的
-If I could have some material. -You are many things.
但唠叨不是我所想要的
Not the least of which is repetitious.
-但他们只是孩子呀 -是的
-But they're children! -Yes.
而我是他们的爸爸
And I'm their father.
晚安
Good night.
♪ 女孩们穿着白衣佩着蓝缎带... ♪
♪ Girls in white dresses With blue satin sashes ♪
♪ 当狗咬时 当蜜蜂蛰时 ♪
♪ When the dog bites When the bee stings ♪
♪ 当我感觉伤心时 ♪
♪ When I'm feeling sad ♪
♪ 我只要想起我最喜爱的事物 ♪
♪ I simply remember my favorite things ♪
♪ 我的心情就不会 ♪
♪ and then I don't feel... ♪
♪ 如此糟了 ♪
♪ ...so bad ♪
看这边
Children, over here. See!
走吧！走
Come on.
玛丽亚小姐
Fraülein Maria?
我们能每天都如此吗？
Can we do this every day?
-你不懧为你会厌倦吗？露易莎 -我想是吧！
-Don't you think you'd get tired of it? -I suppose so.
那每隔一天？
Every other day?
自从在约瑟芬小姐的牙刷上放胶水后 我就没有如此开心过了
I haven't had so much fun since we put glue on Fraülein Josephine's toothbrush.
我真不懂像你们如此好的小孩 怎会恶作剧呢？
I can't understand how children as nice as you can play such tricks.
-这很简单啊 -为何要如此？
-It's easy. -But why do it?
否则我们要如何吸引 爸爸的注意力呢？
How else can we get father's attention?
我明白了
Oh, I see.
我们得多想想办法
We'll have to think about that one.
来吧 大家 过来
All right, over here.
我们要做什么？
What are we going to do?
我们来想首歌 好欢迎男爵夫人的到来
Think of a song for the baroness.
爸爸不喜欢我们唱歌
Father doesn't like us to sing.
或许我们可以改变他的想法 你们会唱什么歌
Perhaps we can change his mind. Now, what songs do you know?
我们什么歌都不会唱
We don't know any songs.
-一首歌都不会？ -我们甚至不知如何唱歌
-Not any? -We don't even know how to sing.
那就不能浪费时间了 你们必须学习
Well... let's not lose time. You must learn.
但是如何学呢？
But how?
♪ 我们从最初步开始学 ♪
♪ Let's start at the very beginning ♪
♪ 很美好的地方开始 ♪
♪ a very good place to start ♪
♪ 当你读书时 你开始从 ♪
♪ When you read you begin with ♪
♪ A B C ♪
♪ A, B, C ♪
♪ 当你唱歌时 你先从 DO RE MI 开始 ♪
♪ When you sing, you begin with Do-Re-Mi ♪
♪ DO RE MI ♪
♪ Do-re-mi ♪
♪ DO RE MI 刚好是最先开始的音 ♪
♪ , Do-re-mi, the first three notes just happen to be ♪
♪ DO RE MI ♪
♪ Do-re-mi ♪
♪ DO RE MI FA SO LA TI ♪
♪ Do-re-mi-fa-so-la-ti ♪
♪ 让我看是否能使它容易点 ♪
♪ Let's see if I can make it easier. ♪
♪ DOE 是鹿 一只小母鹿 ♪
♪ Doe, a deer a female deer ♪
♪ RAY 是一束金色的阳光 ♪
♪ Ray, a drop of golden sun ♪
♪ ME 是对自己的称呼 ♪
♪ Me, a name I call myself ♪
♪ FAR 是很远的长路 ♪
♪ Far, a long long way to run ♪
♪ SEW 是穿针缝衣服 ♪
♪ Sew, a needle pulling thread ♪
♪ LA 是 SO 的小跟班 ♪
♪ La, a note to follow sew ♪
♪ TEA 是茶配果酱面包 ♪
♪ Tea, a drink with jam and bread ♪
♪ 那使我们又回到 DOE ♪
♪ that will bring us back to doe ♪
♪ -DOE！ -是鹿 一只小母鹿 ♪
♪ -Doe -A deer, a female deer ♪
♪ -RAY！ -是一束金色的阳光 ♪
♪ -Ray -A drop of golden sun ♪
♪ -ME！ -是对自己的称呼 ♪
♪ -Me -A name I call myself ♪
♪ -FAR！ -是很远的长路 ♪
♪ -Far -A long long way to run ♪
♪ -SEW！ -是穿针缝衣服 ♪
♪ Sew, a needle pulling thread ♪
♪ -LA！ -是 SO 的小跟班 ♪
♪ -La -A note to follow sew ♪
♪ -TEA！ -是茶配果酱面包 ♪
♪ -Tea -A drink With jam and bread ♪
♪ 那使我们又回到DOE... ♪
♪ that will bring us back to ♪
♪ -DOE！ -是鹿 一只小母鹿 ♪
♪ -Doe -A deer, a female deer ♪
♪ -RAY！ -是一束金色的阳光 ♪
♪ Ray, a drop of golden sun ♪
♪ -ME！ -是对自己的称呼 ♪
♪ Me, a name I call myself ♪
♪ -FAR！ -是很远的长路 ♪
♪ Far, a long long way to run ♪
♪ -SEW！ -是穿针缝衣服 ♪
♪ Sew, a needle pulling thread ♪
♪ -LA！ -是 SO 的小跟班 ♪
♪ La, a note to follow sew ♪
♪ -TEA！ -是茶配果酱面包 ♪
♪ Tea, a drink with jam and bread ♪
♪ 那使我们又回到 DOE... ♪
♪ that will bring us back to doe ♪
♪ DO RE MI FA SO LA TI DO SO DO ♪
♪ Do-re-mi-fa-so-la-ti-do, so-do ♪
好 孩子们 DO RE MI FA SO 只是个来唱歌的工具
Now, children, Do-re-mi-fa-so and so on are only the tools we use to build a song.
只要你们学会音符 就能唱各种歌
Once you have them in your head you can sing different tunes...
把它们凑起来 像这个
...by mixing them up. Like this:
♪ SO DO LA FA MI DO RE ♪
♪ So-do-la-fa-mi-do-re ♪
你们会唱吗？
Can you do that?
♪ SO DO LA FA MI DO RE ♪
♪ So-do-la-fa-mi-do-re ♪
♪ So-do-la-ti-do-re-do ♪
♪ SO DO LA TI DO RE DO ♪
现在凑在一起
Now, put it all together.
♪ SO DO LA FA MI DO RE ♪
♪ So-do-la-fa-mi-do-re ♪
♪ SO DO LA TI DO RE DO ♪
♪ So-do-la-ti-do-re-do ♪
-很好 -但是不具有意义
-Good. -But it doesn't mean anything.
所以我们要加上词 每一音符一个字
So we put in words. One word for every note.
像这样
Like this:
♪ 当你知道音符后 ♪
♪ When you know the notes to sing ♪
♪ 就可随兴唱歌了 ♪
♪ You can sing most anything ♪
一起来
Together!
♪ 当你知道音符后 ♪
♪ When you know the notes to sing ♪
♪ 就可随兴唱歌了 ♪
♪ You can sing most anything ♪
♪ -DOE！ -是鹿 一只小母鹿 ♪
♪ -Doe -A deer, a female deer ♪
♪ -RAY！ -是一束金色的阳光 ♪
♪ -Ray -A drop of golden sun ♪
♪ -ME！ -是对自己的称呼 ♪
♪ -Me -A name I call myself ♪
♪ -FAR！ -是很远的长路 ♪
♪ -Far -A long long way to run ♪
♪ -SEW！ -是穿针缝衣服 ♪
♪ -Sew -A needle pulling thread ♪
♪ -LA！ -是 SO 的小跟班 ♪
♪ -La -A note to follow sew ♪
♪ TEA！ -是茶配果酱面包 ♪
♪ -Tea -A drink With jam and bread ♪
♪ 那使我们又回到 DOE... ♪
♪ that will bring us back to doe ♪
♪ 当你知道音符后 ♪
♪ When you know the notes to sing ♪
♪ 就可随兴唱歌了 ♪
♪ You can sing most anything ♪
♪ -DOE！ -是鹿 一只小母鹿 ♪
♪ Doe a deer, a female deer ♪
♪ -RAY！ -是一束金色的阳光 ♪
♪ Ray a drop of golden sun ♪
♪ -ME！ -是对自己的称呼 ♪
♪ Me a name I call myself ♪
♪ -FAR！ -是很远的长路 ♪
♪ Far a long long way to run ♪
♪ -SEW！ -是穿针缝衣服 ♪
♪ Sew a needle pulling thread ♪
♪ -LA！ -是 SO 的小跟班 ♪
♪ La a note to follow sew ♪
♪ -TEA！ -是茶配果酱面包 ♪
♪ Tea a drink with jam and bread ♪
♪ 那使我们又回到 DOE... ♪
♪ that will bring us back to ♪
♪ SO DO LA FA MI DO RE ♪
♪ So-do-la-fa-mi-do-re ♪
♪ SO DO LA FA TI... ♪
♪ So-do-la-fa-ti ♪
♪ LA SO ♪
♪ La-so ♪
♪ TI DO ♪
♪ Ti-do ♪
♪ SO DO ♪
♪ So-do ♪
这些山真是壮观 盖尔 真是棒透了
The mountains are magnificent, really magnificent.
我特别为你造设的 达令
-I had them put up just for you. -Oh?
万尺高山 盖尔总是相信
Even if it's to a height of 10,000 feet...
它的升起是为了特殊场合
...Georg always believes in "rising to the occasion."
麦斯 你的笑话不改进的话 我就要收回邀请了
Improve the jokes or I'll disinvite you.
你并未邀请我 我是不请自来的
You didn't invite me. I invited myself.
-很自然 -你需要监护人
-Naturally. -You needed a chaperone...
我需要有佳肴
...and I needed a place where the cuisine is superb...
美酒的地方
...the wine cellar unexcelled...
而价格又公道
...and the price perfect.
麦斯 你真的太过份了
Max, you are outrageous.
一点也不 我是很迷人的食客
Not at all. I'm a very charming sponge.
听
Listen.
那是可普曼修道院的唱诗班
That's the Klopmann Monastery Choir.
他们唱得很好
They're good.
非常好
Very good.
以后几天里 我要探访这地区
I must explore this area in the next few days.
某处 有个渴望被发掘的合唱团 在等我发掘
Somewhere, a hungry singing group is waiting for Max Detweiler...
在萨尔兹堡的音乐节时一举成名
...to pluck it out and make it famous at the Salzburg Folk Festival.
-他们成名而你就得利 -那不公平 我得承懧
-They get fame, you get money. -It's unfair, I admit it.
但那天一切都会改变的 我也会成名的
But someday that'll be changed. I shall get the fame too.
天啊 这是怎么回事？
Good heavens, what's this?
没什么 只是本地的顽童
It's nothing. just some local urchins.
这地方真是太美了 又和你在一起
This really is exciting for me, Georg. Being here with you.
树林 湖泽 山峦... 它们都是一样的
Trees, lakes, you've seen them before.
你明白我的意思
That is not what I mean, and you know it.
-你不是指我令你兴奋？ -不可能吗？
-You mean me? I'm exciting? -Is that so impossible?
不是 只是不会发生
No, just highly improbable.
-又来了 又看低自己了 -我是危险的驾驶人
-There you go, running yourself down. -Well, I'm a dangerous driver.
在这里 盖尔 你看来没这么像个谜
You're much less of a riddle when I see you here, Georg.
-在我生长的地方 -是的 正是
-in my natural habitat? -Yes, exactly.
你是说在这
Are you saying that I'm more at home...
鸟语花香的地方
...among the birds and the flowers and the wind that moves...
我感觉较舒适
...through the trees like a restless sea?
多有诗意啊
How poetic.
是的 我是的 不是吗？
Yes, it was rather, wasn't it?
我在此比在维也纳觉得安逸 在你们那奢华的沙龙里
More at home here than in Vienna in all your glittering salons...
和那些无聊汉附庸风雅喝香槟
...gossiping gaily with bores I detest, soaking myself in champagne...
被华尔兹所牵绊
...stumbling about to waltzes by Strausses I can't even remember?
-你就是想告诉我这些吗？ -多少是吧 是的
-Is that what you're saying? -Yes.
你为何会有那概念？
Now whatever gave you that idea?
我真的喜欢这儿 盖尔 如此可爱和宁静
Oh, I do like it here, Georg. It's so lovely and peaceful.
你怎舍得如此常离开此地
How can you leave it so often?
我想是假装自己还是很活跃
Oh, pretending to be madly active, I suppose.
活跃是建议生命充满了目的
Activity suggests a life filled with purpose.
可能是在逃避回忆
Could it be running away from memories?
也许是在寻求留下的理由
Or perhaps just searching for a reason to stay.
我希望那是你常去维也纳的理由
I hope that's why you've been coming to Vienna so often.
-还是那儿有让你着魔的事物？ -我不能说是你令我着魔的
-Were there other distractions? -I'd hardly call you a distraction.
那你如何形容我 盖尔？
Well, what would you call me, Georg?
漂亮...
Lovely...
美丽 聪明有风度 很完美的女主人
...charming, witty, graceful, the perfect hostess...
你会恨我这样说的
...and, you're going to hate me for this...
有点像是我的救世主
...in a way, my savior.
真不浪漫呀
Oh, how unromantic.
如果我不告诉你 那我就是不知感恩的小人了
I'd be an ungrateful wretch if I didn't say...
是你使我重新体会生命的意义
...that you brought some meaning back into my life.
我想我是受宠若惊
I am amusing, I suppose.
而我是有维也纳最好的地方 最上流社交圈的朋友
I have the finest couturier in Vienna and a glittering circle of friends.
-和最豪华的派对 -喔 是啊！
-I do give some rather gay parties. -Oh, yes.
除去那些
But take all that away...
你只有财富和一位飘浮不定的我
...and you have just wealthy, unattached little me...
在寻寻觅觅像你一样的人
...searching, just like you.
多来点甜点吗？
More strudel, Herr Detweiler?
-我吃了多少？ -两个了
-how many have I had? -Two.
那么它就成为第三个吧
Make it an uneven three.
还在吃 麦斯？一定是不太快乐
Still eating, Max? Must be unhappy.
数月来 我一直想从 何洛克那边弄来四部曲
That mixed quartet I've been trying to steal away from Sol Hurok...
-发生何事 达令？ -昨天 沙夏皮特抢先了
-What happened? -...Sascha Petrie stole them first.
我最恨的莫过于贼了
I hate thieves.
麦斯 你要学习自爱
Max, you really must try and learn to love yourself.
为此事我得打长途电话到巴黎
I had to call Paris, Rome and Stockholm.
-当然是用盖尔的电话了 -要不然我怎么负担的起
-On Georg's telephone, of course. -How else could I afford it?
我喜欢有钱人 喜欢他们的生活方式 尤其和他们一起生活时
I like rich people, the way they live and how I live when I'm with them.
我在想孩子们上哪儿去了？
I wonder where the children are.
显然地 他们一定是 听见我来了 躲起来了
They must have heard I was coming and hid.
我是希望他们会在家欢迎你的
I was hoping they'd be here to welcome you.
麦斯 试着放开朗一些 好吗？
Max, do step out of character for a moment and try and be charming.
怎样？
Well?
什么怎样？
Well what?
你让盖尔决定了没？ 我是否会听见婚礼钟声？
Have you made up his mind? Do I hear wedding bells?
-很有希望 -太棒了
-Pealing madly. -Marvelous.
-但不一定有婚礼 -那是什么意思？
-Not necessarily for me. -What kind of talk's that?
那跟你无关 麦斯
None-of-your-business talk.
我很喜欢盖尔 我不准你把我们当玩具
I'm terribly fond of him, so don't toy with us.
但当我是孩子时 我喜欢玩具 所以告诉我一切吧
But I'm a child. I like toys. So tell me everything.
快点 告诉麦斯一切的细节
Come on. Tell me every teensy-weensy, intimate, disgusting detail.
我们可以说 我有感觉 我可能会被懧可
Well, let's just say I have a feeling I may be here on approval.
-我同意 你怎会错过？ -很容易的
-I approve of that. how can you miss? -Far too easily.
如我了解你的话 达令 我知道你会找到方法的
If I know you, darling, and I do, you will find a way.
他不是普通人 他很富有
-He's no ordinary man. -No, he's rich.
当他老婆死后 给他带来他可怕的心痛
His wife's death gave him a great heartache.
当你先生死时 他留给你一笔“可怕”的遗产
And your husband's death gave you a great fortune.
麦斯 你真是怪物
Oh, Max, you really are a beast.
你和盖尔对我来讲就像是一家人 所以我想看到你们两人结婚
You and Georg are like family. That's why I want to see you married.
我们必须保留那笔钱 在同一家庭中
We must keep all that lovely money in the family.
-你在干什么？ -范舰长
-What are you doing there? -Oh, captain von Trapp.
我正在找...
I was just looking for... .
我没看到你 我不知道你...
I didn't see, I mean, I didn't know you were--
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler!
你是谁？
Who are you?
我送电报给德维勒先生
I have a telegram for Herr Detweiler.
-我就是 -是的 先生
-I am Herr Detweiler. -Yes, sir.
好 电报你送到了 滚吧
You've delivered your telegram. Now get out.
-盖尔 他只是个小男孩 -是 而我只是奥国人
-Georg, he's just a boy. -Yes, and I'm just an Austrian.
要发生的迟早会发生 只要确定不会发生在你身上
Things will happen. Make sure they don't happen to you.
麦斯 你千万别再这样说
Max! Don't you ever say that again.
你知道我没有政治主张
I have no political convictions.
-我能帮上什么吗？ -是的 你可以帮忙的
-can I help It If other people do? -You can help it.
你非帮不可
You must help it.
哈啰
Hello?
你如此遥远 你在哪儿？
You're far away. Where are you?
在一个遥不可及的世界里
In a world that's disappearing, I'm afraid.
有办法带你回到现实世界吗？
Is there any way I could bring you back to the world I'm in?
-爸爸！爸爸！ -你们的爸爸！
-Father! Father! -There's your father!
哦 舰长 你回来了
Oh, captain, you're home!
立刻从水里上来
Come out of that water at once!
你一定是史蕾特男爵夫人
Oh, you must be Baroness Schraeder.
我湿透了！
I'm soaked to the skin!
排好
Straight line!
这位是史蕾特男爵夫人
This is Baroness Schraeder.
而这些
And these...
是我的孩子们
...are my children.
你们好
How do you do?
进屋去洗干净、换件衣服 再回来这里 立刻！
Go inside, dry off, clean up, change your clothes and report back here!
小姐 请你留下来
Fraülein, you will stay here, please!
我最好去看麦斯在干什么
I think I'd better go see what Max is up to.
现在 小姐
Now, Fraülein...
我要你据实回答
...I want a truthful answer.
是的 舰长
Yes, captain.
是真有可能？我只是刚想到的
Is it possible, or could I have just imagined it?
我的孩子们今天有爬过树吗？
Have my children, by any chance, been climbing trees today?
是的 舰长
Yes, captain.
这样
I see.
我能否请教他们哪来的这些？
And where, may I ask, did they get these... .
-游戏服 -你是如此称呼它们的？
-Play clothes. -Is that What They are?
是我拿我卧房里的旧窗帘所做的
I made them from the drapes that used to hang in my bedroom.
-窗帘 -还剩下很多
-Drapes? -They have plenty of wear left.
孩子们穿着玩了不少地方
We've been everywhere in them.
你是在告诉我 我的孩子穿着旧窗帘的布料
Are you telling me that my children have been roaming about Salzburg...
玩遍了萨尔兹堡
...dressed up in nothing but some old drapes?
是的 而且玩得很开心
And having a marvelous time!
-他们有制服 -对不起那是疯子穿的
-They have uniforms. -Forgive me, straitjackets.
孩子们不该担心 会弄脏珍贵的制服
They can't be children if they worry about clothes--
我没听过埋怨
They don't complain.
他们不敢 他们太爱你
They don't dare. They love you too much and fear--
我不希望在此情况下讨论我的孩子
Don't discuss my children.
你必须听 你都不在家久留
You've got to hear, you're never home--
我说过不喜欢听你说
I don't want to hear more!
我知道你不要 但你必须
I know you don't, but you've got to!
-就拿莉莎来说吧... -你别再说有关莉莎一句
-Liesl's not a child. -Not one word--
她有天会成为女人 而你甚至不了解她
Soon she'll be a woman and you won't even know her.
费瑞克想要成为一个男人 却没有人给他作榜样
Friedrich wants to be a man but you're not here to show--
你胆敢说我儿子的事
Don't you dare tell me--
碧姬塔能告诉你这些 她知道一切事情
Brigitta could tell you about him. She notices everything.
还有寇特 当你忽略他时 他假装坚强 隐藏伤痛
Kurt acts tough to hide the pain when you ignore him...
你总是这样对待他们
...the way you do all of them.
还有露易莎 我还不了解她 但总有人要去了解她
Louisa, I don't know about yet.
还有最小的 她只想要被爱 求求你 舰长 爱他们
The little ones just want love. Please, love them all.
我不想再听你说有关孩子的事
I don't care to hear more.
-我还没说完 -是的 你说完了
-I am not finished yet, captain! -Oh, yes, you are, captain!
小姐
Fraülein.
你现在立刻收拾行李
Now, you will pack your things this minute...
回去修道院
...and return to the abbey.
那是什么？
What's that?
有人在唱歌
It's singing.
我知道 但是谁在唱歌？
Yes, I realize it's singing. But who is singing?
孩子们
The children.
The children?
我教他们一首歌欢迎男爵夫人
I taught them something to sing for the baroness.
♪ 我心雀跃不已 只因它拾得片音短曲 ♪
♪ My heart wants to sing every song it hears ♪
♪ 只因它拾得片音短曲 ♪
♪ Every song that it hears ♪
♪ 我心澎湃狂喜 宛如鸟生新羽展翅飞去 ♪
♪ My heart wants to beat like the wings of the birds that rise ♪
♪ 自湖滨遥向枝头高栖 ♪
♪ from the lake to the trees ♪
♪ 向枝头高栖 ♪
♪ To the trees ♪
♪ 我心呢喃低语仿佛钟铃 ♪
♪ My heart wants to sigh Like a chime that flies ♪
♪ 自教堂乘风徐徐而来 ♪
♪ from a church on a breeze ♪
♪ 欢笑一如小溪清清 蜿蜒宛转 ♪
♪ To laugh like a brook When it trips and falls ♪
♪ 川流石头间 ♪
♪ Over stones on its way ♪
♪ On its way ♪
♪ 彻夜高歌 ♪
♪ To sing through the night ♪
♪ 就像云雀习祷 喜悦轻盈 ♪
♪ Like a lark who is learning to pray ♪
♪ 我总会来这山巅 ♪
♪ I go to the hills ♪
♪ 每当我心抑郁 ♪
♪ When my heart is lonely ♪
♪ 我知道定能听见 ♪
♪ I know I will hear ♪
♪ 昔日歌声 ♪
♪ What I've heard before ♪
♪ 我心将被赐福 ♪
♪ My heart will be blessed ♪
♪ 只因这天籁之音 ♪
♪ With the sound of music ♪
♪ 我也愿... ♪
♪ and I'll sing... ♪
♪ 再次高歌 ♪
♪ ...once more ♪
薄雪草
Edelweiss!
你从来没有告诉我 你的孩子们如此地可爱
You never told me how enchanting your children are.
别走开
Don't go away.
小姐
Fraülein.
我...
I...
我的表现很失常 我道歉
...behaved badly. I apologize.
不 是我说话太过份了 这是我最大的缺点
I'm far too outspoken. It's one of my worst faults.
你说的对
You were right.
我不了解我的孩子们
I don't know my children.
你还有时间 舰长 他们很想亲近你
There's still time, captain. They want so much to be close to you.
你将音乐带回到这个家
And you brought music back into the house.
我都忘记了
I'd forgotten.
小姐
Fraülein.
我要你留下来
I want you to stay.
我请求你留下来
I ask you to stay.
-如果我能帮忙的话 -你已经帮了很多忙了
-If I could be of any help. -You have already.
只是你不自知
More than you know.
玛塔
Marta.
开幕
Curtain!
♪ 高山上有个寂寞牧羊人 ♪
♪ High on a hill was a lonely goatherd ♪
♪ 他的歌声真响亮 ♪
♪ Loud was the voice of the lonely goatherd ♪
♪ 偏僻的小镇居民也听到了 ♪
♪ Folks in a town that was quite remote heard ♪
♪ 他的歌声雄壮而清脆 ♪
♪ Lusty and clear from the goatherd's throat heard ♪
玛塔！玛塔！
Marta. Marta!
葛特儿 王子
Gretl, the prince!
♪ 城堡桥上的王子听到了 ♪
♪ A prince on the bridge of a castle moat heard ♪
♪ 登山的人们也听到了 ♪
♪ Men on a road With a load to tote heard ♪
♪ 咖啡店的人也听到了 ♪
♪ Men in the midst of a table d'h óte heard ♪
♪ 喝啤酒的人们也听到了 ♪
♪ Men drinking beer With the foam afloat heard ♪
♪ 穿淡粉色外衣的女孩也听见了 ♪
♪ One little girl ln a pale pink coat heard ♪
♪ 她向那寂寞牧羊人唱出她的心声 ♪
♪ She yodeled back To the lonely goatherd ♪
♪ 她妈妈也欣喜地唱着 ♪
♪ Soon her mama With a gleaming gloat heard ♪
♪ 女孩和牧羊人 美好二重唱呀 ♪
♪ What a duet for a girl and goatherd ♪
♪ 穿淡粉色外衣的女孩也听见了 ♪
♪ One little girl ln a pale pink coat heard ♪
♪ 她向那寂寞的牧羊人唱出她的心声 ♪
♪ She yodeled back To the lonely goatherd ♪
♪ 她妈妈也欣喜地唱着 ♪
♪ Soon her mama With a gleaming gloat heard ♪
♪ 女孩和牧羊人 美好的二重唱呀 ♪
♪ What a duet for a girl and goatherd ♪
♪ 他们欢天喜地 ♪
♪ Happy are they ♪
♪ 二重唱很快变成三重唱 ♪
♪ Soon the duet will become a trio ♪
好极了！好极了！
-Bravo! -Bravo!
真是太好了
Very good!
真是美妙
Wonderful!
-麦斯伯伯 我们可以留下傀儡吗？ -是啊 可以吗？
-can we keep the puppets, Uncle Max? -Yes, can we?
你当然可以 亲爱的
Of course you may, my darlings.
不然 我怎能会叫可伦教授 将帐单寄给你爸爸呢？
Why else did I tell Professor Kohner to send the bill to your father?
干的好！小姐
Well done, Fraülein.
我真的很感动
I really am very much impressed.
他们是你的孩子
They're your children, captain.
你还有什么做不到的事吗？
My dear, is there anything you can't do?
我想做个好修女有些困难
Well, I'm not sure I'll make a good nun.
如果有任何问题 我很乐意帮你的
If you have any problems, I'd be happy to help you.
各位请注意
Attention, everyone!
我有惊人的事情要宣布 惊喜！惊喜！
I have an announcement to make. Surprise! Surprise!
经过一番苦心的寻求
Today, after a long and desperate search...
我终于找到参加 萨尔兹堡音乐节的合唱团了
...I have found a most exciting entry for the Salzburg Folk Festival.
恭禧你 麦斯
Congratulations, Max.
这回是哪个团雀屏中选呢？
And who will you be exploiting this time?
-圣伊格森合唱团 -再猜
-The Saint lgnatius Choir? -Guess again.
我想 克兰曼歌唱团
Well, let me see now. the Klopmann Choir?
-不对 不对 -不对吗？
-No, No, No, no. -No, no?
告诉我们
Tell us.
一个由家庭组成的合唱团
A singing group all in one family. You'll never guess, Georg.
多么好的主意
What a charming idea!
谁的家庭？
Whose family?
你的啊！
Yours.
他们将会是一大轰动
They'll be the talk of the festival.
-有何好笑的？ -你很好笑 麦斯
-Well, now, what's so funny? -You are, Max.
昂贵 但很好笑
You're expensive, but very funny.
-他们一定会轰动的 -不 麦斯
-They'll be a sensation! -No, Max.
这是极好的主意 新面孔又自然
It's a wonderful idea. Fresh, original.
麦斯 我的孩子们不公开演唱
Max! My children do not sing in public.
不能怪我没尝试过
You can't blame me for trying.
孩子们 下一个该谁唱？
Children, who shall we hear from next?
谁？
Who?
好
Yes.
全体一致通过
The vote is unanimous.
由你演唱 舰长
You, captain.
我？
Me?
-我不懂 -拜托
-I don't understand. -Please.
不...
No, no, no, no.
我听说 很久以前 你唱得非常好
I'm told that you were quite good.
-那是非常非常久之前 -我还记得 爸爸
-that was a very, very long time ago. -I remember, father.
-请为我们唱一首 -求求你 爸爸
-Play us something we know. -Oh, please, father.
嗯...
Well... .
-你怎么没跟我说 -说什么？
-Why didn't you tell me? -What?
要带我的口琴来
To bring along my harmonica.
♪ 薄雪草 ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ 每日清晨你向我打招呼 ♪
♪ Every morning you greet me ♪
♪ 小又白 ♪
♪ Small and white ♪
♪ 洁而亮 ♪
♪ Clean and bright ♪
♪ 你很高兴 ♪
♪ You look happy... ♪
♪ 遇见我 ♪
♪ ... to meet me ♪
♪ 雪白的花朵 ♪
♪ Blossom of snow ♪
♪ 愿你绽放、茁壮 ♪
♪ May you bloom and grow ♪
♪ 永远盛开 永远成长 ♪
♪ Bloom and grow forever ♪
♪ 薄雪草 ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ 永远祝福我的故乡 ♪
♪ Bless my homeland forever ♪
♪ -薄雪草！ -薄雪草！ ♪
♪ -Edelweiss -Edelweiss ♪
♪ 每日清晨你向我打招呼 ♪
♪ Every morning you greet me ♪
♪ -小又白！ -小又白！ ♪
♪ -Small and white -Small and white ♪
♪ -洁而亮！ -洁而亮！ ♪
♪ -Clean and bright -Clean and bright ♪
♪ 你很高兴 ♪
♪ You look happy... ♪
♪ 遇见我 ♪
♪ ... to meet me ♪
♪ 雪白的花朵 ♪
♪ Blossom of snow ♪
♪ 愿你绽放、茁壮 ♪
♪ May you bloom and grow ♪
♪ 永远盛开 永远成长 ♪
♪ Bloom and grow forever ♪
♪ 薄雪草 ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ 永远祝福我的故乡 ♪
♪ Bless my homeland forever ♪
只要你随时开口 你可以参加我的新节目
Anytime you say the word, Georg, you can be part of my new act:
范崔普家庭合唱团
The von Trapp Family Singers.
我有个好主意
I have a wonderful idea, Georg.
让此屋中充满音乐
Let's really fill this house with music.
当我在此期间 你要为我开个盛大的舞会
You must give a grand and glorious party for me.
-舞会？ -好啦爸爸 拜托你
-A party? -Yes, father, please!
是的 我想我该懧识 你在萨尔兹堡的朋友了
It's high time I met all your friends...
也让他们见见我 你不同意吗？
...and they met me. Don't you agree?
-我明白你的意思 -喔 拜托拜托...
-I see what you mean. -Oh, please!
孩子们 该上床了 道晚安吧
Children, it's bedtime. Come now, say good night.
晚安 爸爸
Good night, father.
-晚安 -晚安 男爵夫人
-Good night. -Good night, Baroness Schraeder.
晚安 爸爸
Good night, father.
晚安 麦斯伯伯
Good night, Uncle Max.
那将会是我的第一次舞会 爸爸
It'll be my first party, father!
-舰长 -男爵夫人 这位是赫尔
-Captain. -Herr Zeller. Baroness Schraeder.
-你好 赫尔 -男爵夫人
-Good evening, Herr Zeller. -Baroness.
你好
How do you do? Good evening.
我想你注意到大厅上 挂着奥国国旗
Did you notice the obvious display of the Austrian flag?
女人们看来好漂亮
The women look so beautiful.
我觉得她们好丑
I think they look ugly.
你只是如此说 因为你怕她们
You're just scared of them.
傻瓜！只有成人才会怕女人
Silly, only grown-up men fear women.
-我懧为男人看来好美 -你怎么会知道？
-I think the men look beautiful. -How would you know?
莉莎 你在跟谁跳舞
Liesl, who are you dancing with?
没有人
Nobody.
哦 你有的
Oh, yes, you are.
我有这份荣幸吗？
May I have this dance?
我很乐意的 年轻人
I'd be delighted, young man.
你们为何不告诉我 你们会跳舞
Why didn't you tell me you could dance?
我们怕你会叫我们一起跳舞 范崔普家庭舞蹈团
We feared you'd make us all dance. the von Trapp Family Dancers.
他们在演奏什么？
What are they playing?
那是奥国的一种民俗舞
It's the Laendler. an Austrian folk dance.
-教我们 -我很小时候学的
-Show me. -I haven't danced since I was little.
你记得的 求求你
You remember. Please?
-嗯... -拜托嘛
-Well... . -Please.
好吧 过来
All right. Come on over here.
现在你鞠躬 我答礼
Now you bow and I curtsy.
-像这样 -很好 现在我们走几步！
-Like this? -Fine. Now we go for a little walk.
123 123
One, two, three. One, two, three.
123 一起踏步 踏步跳...转圈
One, two, three, step together. Now, step hop, step hop.
这边 踏步跳...转圈
Now turn under. Not quite.
This way. Hop step, hop... and under.
寇特 我们还要多练习
Kurt, we'll have to practice.
容许我来跳好吗？
Do allow me, will you?
后面的我不记得了
I don't remember anymore.
-你的脸好红 -是吗？
-Your face is all red. -Is it?
我想我不习惯跳舞吧
I don't suppose I'm used to dancing.
那真是跳得太棒了
Why, that was beautifully done.
你们是迷人的一对
What a lovely couple you make.
我想孩子们该上床了
It's time the children said good night.
是的 我们马上去前厅
We'll be in the hall.
-我们有特别节目 对不对？ -对！
-We have something special prepared. -Right!
是的 快点
Yes, come on!
盖尔 你无需担心
All that needless worrying, Georg.
以为舞会上找不到朋友
You thought you wouldn't find a friend at the party.
-今晚外面有点凉 是不是？ -我不知道
-A bit chilly out tonight, isn't it? -Oh, I don't know.
似乎有些暖和呢！
It seemed rather warm to me.
先生女士们！
Ladies and gentlemen.
范崔普舰长的孩子 希望向各位道晚安
The children of Captain von Trapp wish to say good night to you.
♪ 忧愁的钟声来自大厅 ♪
♪ There's a sad sort of clanging from the clock in the hall ♪
♪ 钟声也响起了 ♪
♪ and the bells in the steeple too ♪
♪ 在孩子们卧室里 一只滑稽的小鸟 ♪
♪ and up in the nursery an absurd little bird ♪
♪ 伸出舌头来道“咕咕” ♪
♪ Is popping up to say "coo-coo" ♪
♪ 咕咕 ♪
♪ Coo-coo ♪
♪ 他们很遗憾地催我们离开 ♪
♪ Regretfully they tell us ♪
♪ 又坚定地告诉我们 ♪
♪ But firmly they compel us ♪
♪ 要我们向大家 ♪
♪ To say goodbye ♪
♪ 道晚安 ♪
♪ To you ♪
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell Auf Wiedersehen, good night ♪
♪ 我不愿离开这个美景 ♪
♪ I hate to go and leave this pretty sight ♪
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell, Auf Wiedersehen, adieu ♪
♪ 我临去叹息 说声再见 ♪
♪ Adieu, adieu To you and you and you ♪
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell Au revoir, auf Wiedersehen ♪
♪ 我能否留下喝第一口香槟 ♪
♪ I'd like to stay and taste my first champagne ♪
-可以吗？ -不行
-Yes? -No.
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell Auf Wiedersehen, goodbye ♪
♪ 我真的很难过我必须道再见... ♪
♪ I leave and heave a sigh and say goodbye ♪
♪ 再见... ♪
♪ Goodbye ♪
♪ 我真高兴可以离去 ♪
♪ I'm glad to go ♪
♪ 我不能说谎 ♪
♪ I cannot tell a lie ♪
♪ 我展翅！我飘浮！ ♪
♪ I flit, I float ♪
♪ 我在飞翔！ ♪
♪ I fleetly flee, I fly ♪
♪ 太阳已安眠 ♪
♪ the sun has gone to bed ♪
♪ 我也必须睡觉 ♪
♪ and so must I ♪
♪ 别了 ♪
♪ So long ♪
♪ 再见 ♪
♪ Farewell ♪
♪ 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ Auf Wiedersehen, goodbye ♪
♪ 晚安！ ♪
♪ Goodbye ♪
他们真是不同凡响 想想在音乐节的成绩
Extraordinary! What they'd do at the festival.
年轻女士 我必须跟你谈谈
Young lady, I must have a word with you.
盖尔 你不能让她离去的 她必须参加派对
Georg, you won't let this girl get away. She must join the party.
-不 我真的... 别说了
-No, really l-- -Stop. Stop It now.
-盖尔 拜托 -如你愿意的话 可以留下来
-Georg, please. -You can if you want to, Fraülein.
我坚持 你会是我今晚的女伴
I insist. You will be my dinner partner.
-这是生意 -福兰斯
This is business. Franz...
在我的座位旁 替玛丽亚小姐加一个位子
...set another place next to mine for Fraülein Maria.
-悉听尊便 -似乎已安排好了
-Whatever you say. -It appears to be all arranged.
-看似如此 -我的打扮不适合
-It does. -I'm not suitably dressed.
你可以换衣服 我们等你
You can change. We'll wait.
舰长 你一定是 很以你的儿女为荣
Captain, you must be very proud of your youngsters.
是的 谢谢你
I am, thank you.
还有什么能比孩子的歌声
Is there a more beautiful expression of what is good in our country...
更能表现我国的优点
...than the innocent voices of our children?
对了 男爵
Oh, come now, baron.
你想要我们相信 只有奥国有独特高尚的品德？
Would you have us believe that Austria holds a monopoly on virtue?
我们有些人喜欢以悠扬歌声
Herr Zeller, some of us prefer Austrian voices raised in song...
对抗丑陋德国的威胁
...to ugly German threats.
鸵鸟喜欢埋首于沙中
The ostrich buries his head in the sand...
有时藏于国旗里
...and sometimes in the flag.
或许有些人警告你 合并就要来临了
Perhaps those who would warn you that the Anschluss is coming, and it is...
而就要来了 舰长 或许会以音乐来跟你打交道呢
...would get further with you by setting their words to music.
如果纳粹占据奥国 你会是整个喇叭队
If the Nazis take over Austria, you will be the entire trumpet section.
你太恭维我了 舰长
You flatter me.
我是多么笨拙 我是要指责你的
Oh, how clumsy of me. I meant to accuse you.
你愿意来协助我 真的太仁慈了 男爵夫人
It's very kind of you to offer to help me, baroness.
我很乐意
I'm delighted, Maria.
但我实在没有任何适合的衣服
I really don't think I have anything that would be appropriate.
那晚你穿的那件迷人衣服呢
Now where is that lovely little thing you were wearing the other evening?
使舰长无法将视线移开你身上
When the captain couldn't keep his eyes off you.
无法转移他的目光？
Couldn't keep his eyes off me?
得了吧 亲爱的 我们都是女人
Come, my dear, we are women.
别再假装我们不知道 男人注意我们
Let's not pretend we don't know when a man notices us.
在此 舰长知道每个人和每件事
-Here we are. -The captain notices everybody.
你无需如此抗拒的 玛丽亚
There's no need to feel so defensive, Maria.
你很迷人 你知道吗？
You are quite attractive, you know.
如果舰长不注意你的话 他就不是男人了
The captain would hardly be a man if he didn't notice you.
男爵夫人 我希望你在开玩笑
Baroness, I hope you're joking.
一点也不！
Not at all.
但我从来没有做过此事
I've never done a thing to--
你无需如此
You don't have to, my dear.
心仪的女人让男人抗拒不了
Nothing's more irresistible to a man than a woman who's in love with him.
-爱他吗？ 是的
-in love With him? -Of course.
他以为他爱上你了
What makes it so nice is he thinks he's in love with you.
但那不是事实
But that's not true.
你当然注意到 他注视你时的眼神吧
Surely you've noticed the way he looks into your eyes.
而且当你和他跳舞时 你在他臂弯中脸都红了
And you know, you blushed in his arms when you were dancing just now.
别太介意
Don't take it to heart.
他很快就会适应的
He'll get over it soon enough, I think.
男人都是如此的
Men do, you know.
那我必须离开了
Then I should go.
我不能留在此地
I mustn't stay here.
-我能帮什么忙吗？ -没有
-is there something I can do to help? -No, Nothing.
有的
Yes.
求你别告诉舰长这件事
Don't say a word to the captain.
不 我一个字也不会提
No, I wouldn't dream of it.
再见 玛丽亚
Goodbye, Maria.
我相信你会成为很好的修女
I'm sure you'll make a very fine nun.
香槟
Champagne, darling.
我觉得该庆祝一下 干杯
I feel like celebrating. Cheers.
-你消息灵通 -或许吧
-you know something. -Perhaps.
如果你如此聪明 告诉我如何要玛丽亚影响盖尔
If you're so clever, tell me how to get Fraülein to influence Georg.
我要这些孩子参加节庆
I want those children in the festival.
这对奥国深具意义的
Elsa, this is important to Austria.
对你也不会有妨害的
Wouldn't do you any harm either.
我曾想过
I thought of that.
谈到影响
Well, if it's a matter of influence...
你该找我谈才对
...maybe the one you have to be talking to is me.
(中场休息)
(进场)
-二 -三
-Two. -Three.
-四 -五
-Four. -Five.
-六 -七
-Six. -Seven.
八
Eight.
-四 -二
-Four. -Two.
-七 -五
-Seven. -Five.
-二 -六
-Two. -Six.
真好玩！
Isn't this fun?
-四 -我是第五
-Four. -I'm number five.
-喔 对 -八
-Oh, yes. -Eight.
-二 -四
-Two. -Four.
六
Six.
二
Two.
夫人 我们累了 不要玩了
Baroness Schraeder, do you mind if we stop now? We're tired.
随便你们
Whatever you want, dear.
明天再玩
We'll do it again tomorrow.
乡间真安静 不是吗？
The country's so restful, isn't it?
喝点柠檬水吧
Have some lemonade.
一定有更容易的办法
There must be an easier way.
想到你做蒳个孩子的妈妈 真令我哭笑不得
I get a fiendish delight thinking of you as the mother of seven.
你计划如何做呢？
How do you plan to do it?
亲爱的 你没听过
Darling, haven't you ever heard...
寄宿学校吗？
...of a delightful little thing called boarding school?
你真狡诈独裁
Baroness Machiavelli.
麦伯伯 爸爸在哪？
Uncle Max, where's Father?
我想他在屋子里
I think he's in the house.
你们为何都闷闷不乐呢？
What's the matter with all you gloomy pussies?
-没什么 -我知道怎么办 我们来练习唱歌
-Nothing. -I know. Let's have a rehearsal.
为了什么呢？
What for?
假装我站在节庆的表演台上
Let's make believe we're on-stage at the festival.
-我不想唱歌 -没有玛丽亚我不想唱
-I don't feel like singing. -Not without Fraülein Maria.
莉莎去拿吉他 快点各位
Liesl, get the guitar. Come on, Marta.
去各就各位 这就对了
Everybody into the group. Get in your places.
高兴点 给我们一点音乐 莉莎
Now be cheerful, right? Give us the key, Liesl.
现在 开始
Now, impress me.
葛特儿 你为何不唱呢？
Gretl, why don't you sing?
我手指痛不能唱
I can't. I've got a sore finger.
但是你在舞会中唱得很好
But you sang so beautifully the night of the party.
来 试试看 唱一唱你会好的
Come on, all of you. Try something you know.
快乐点
Enjoy it. Be cheerful.
好了 莉莎
All right, Liesl.
♪ 大地新象 ♪
♪ the hills are alive ♪
♪ 只因这天籁之声 ♪
♪ With the sound of music ♪
♪ 清歌传唱 ♪
♪ With songs they have sung ♪
♪ 千年万年 ♪
♪ For a thousand years ♪
♪ 云岭送翠 ♪
♪ the hills fill my heart ♪
♪ 只为这天籁之声 ♪
♪ With the sound of music ♪
他们是唱给我听
They wanted to sing for me, bless their hearts.
很好...别停下来
That's lovely, lovely. Don't stop.
-盖尔 你喝点饮料吧 -不 谢谢 达令
-something long and cool, Georg? -No, thank you, darling.
-爸爸 -是的 碧姬塔
-Father? -Yes, Brigitta?
玛丽亚真的不回来了吗？
Is it true Fraülein Maria isn't coming back?
是的 我想是不回来了 有什么好喝吗？
Yes, I suppose it's true. What have we got here?
-粉红柠檬水 -至少有柠檬水
-Pink lemonade. -Laced With lemonade.
爸爸 我不敢相信
I don't believe it, father.
-亲爱的 不相信什么 -关于玛丽亚
-What? -About Fraülein Maria.
哦 玛丽亚
Oh, Fraülein Maria!
我没把她的留言告诉你们吗？ 我确定我说过了
Didn't I tell you what her note said? I'm sure I did.
她说她很想念修道院的人
She said she missed her life at the abbey.
她必须离开我们
She had to leave us.
就这样
And that's all there is to it.
好 我现在想尝点柠檬水
I think I'm brave enough to try some of that.
-她甚至没有告别 -她在留言上有说
-She didn't even say goodbye. -She did in her note.
那是不同的事
That isn't the same thing.
不甜不酸
Not too sweet, not too sour.
只是太粉红了
Just too pink.
爸爸 谁是新的家庭教师？
Father, who is our new governess going to be?
嗯...
Well...
你们再也不会有家庭教师了
...you're not going to have a governess anymore.
-不会有？ -不会
-We're not? -No.
你们将要有个新妈妈
You're going to have a new mother.
一个新妈妈？
A new mother?
我们昨晚谈过了 一切都决定安排好了
We talked about it last night. It's all settled.
我们都将会很快乐
And we're all going to be very happy.
好了...去玩吧
Well, all right, all right. Run off and play.
是的 我的孩子们
Yes, my children?
-我叫莉莎 -是的
-my name is Liesl. -Yes, Liesl?
我们 我的兄弟姐妹 我们要见玛丽亚小姐
We, my brothers and sisters, want to see Fraülein Maria.
小姐？
Fraülein Maria?
哦 玛丽亚
Oh, Maria.
请进来
Come in, please.
在这等一下
Wait here.
我是玛格丽特修女 我知道你们想见玛丽亚
I'm Sister Margaretta. I understand you inquired about Maria.
我们必须见她 请你告诉她我们在这
We have to see her. Will you tell her we're here?
-恐怕我做不到 -你一定要告诉她
-I'm afraid I can't do that. -But you've got to!
-她是我们的家教 -我们要她回来
-She's our governess. -We want her back.
-她甚至没有道别 -这件事很重要
She didn't even say goodbye.
我们只想和她说说话
All we want to do is talk to her.
我很抱歉 孩子们 但是玛丽亚在修行
I'm very sorry, but Maria is in seclusion.
-她不愿见任何人 -她会见我们的
-She hasn't been seeing anyone. -She'll see us.
我要把我的手指给她看
I want to show her my finger.
亲爱的 改天吧
Some other time, dear.
我会告诉她 你们来过
I'll tell her you were here.
-谢谢你们来 -我们要见玛丽亚...
-It was sweet of you to call. -We have to speak to her!
好了 走吧 孩子们 回家吧
Run along, children. Run along home.
我知道她会见我们的
I'm sure she'd like to see us.
玛格丽特修女 求求你
Sister Margaretta, please.
-再见 孩子们 -玛格丽特修女 拜托你...
-Goodbye, children. -Sister Margaretta, may We, please?
那是怎么回事 玛格丽特修女
What was that about, Sister?
院长 范崔普家的孩子
The von Trapp children, Reverend Mother.
他们要见玛丽亚
They want to see Maria.
她说话了没？ 她有没有告诉你发生了什么事？
Has she spoken yet? Has she told you anything?
院长 除了祈祷外 她什么也没说
She doesn't say a word, Reverend Mother, except in prayer.
可怜的孩子
Poor child.
很奇怪 她似乎是很快乐地回来
It's strange. She seems happy to be back here...
但现在似乎又不快乐了
...and yet she's unhappy too.
或许让她离开我们那么久 是错误的
Perhaps I have been wrong in leaving her alone so long.
我想你最好把她带来见我 即使她还没准备好
Bring her to me, even if she's not yet ready.
是的 院长
Yes, Reverend Mother.
加丝特修女 带这位新姐妹到更衣室
Sister Augusta, take our new postulant to the robing room.
愿上帝祝福你 我的女儿！
God bless you, my daughter.
是的 带她进来
Yes, bring her in.
你很不快乐 我很抱歉
You've been unhappy. I'm sorry.
院长
Reverend Mother.
他们为何要你回来？
Why did they send you back to us?
院长 他们没有送我回来 是我主动离开的
They didn't send me back. I left.
坐下 玛丽亚
Sit down, Maria.
告诉我事情的始末
Tell me what happened.
因为我惊恐
I was frightened.
-惊恐 是不是他们对你不好？ -哦 不是
-Frightened? Were they unkind to you. -Oh, no!
我很迷惑
No, I was confused. I felt... .
我从未有那种感觉
I've never felt that way before.
我不能留下来 我知道远离他们会比较安全
I couldn't stay. I knew that here I'd be away from it. I'd be safe.
玛丽亚 我们的修道院 不是用来逃避的
Maria, our abbey is not to be used as an escape.
是什么事 你无法面对
What is it you can't face?
我无法再面对他
I can't face him again.
他？
Him?
谢谢你 玛格丽特修女
Thank you, Sister Margaretta.
是范崔普舰长？
Captain von Trapp?
-你是否爱上他了？ -我不知道...
-Are you in love with him? -I don't know!
我不知道...
I don't know. I--
男爵夫人 她...说他爱上我了
The baroness said I was. She said that he was in love with me.
但我不相信
But I didn't want to believe it.
有时候当我们彼此对看时
There were times we looked at each other.
院长 我简直不能呼吸
I could hardly breathe.
-你让他知道你的感受了吗？ -就算有 我也不知道
-Did you let him see your feelings? -I don't know.
那就是我的苦闷 我去那是上帝的旨意
That's what's torturing me. I was on God's errand.
我们两人相爱会是错的 我不能留下 我就是不能留下
To have asked for his love would have been wrong. I just couldn't stay.
这时候我真的要发誓
I'm ready at this moment to take my vows.
-请帮助我 -玛丽亚
-please help me. -Maria.
男女之间的关系也是神圣的 你有机会得到爱
The love of a man and a woman is holy. You have a great capacity to love.
你必须了解 上帝要你如何地去爱
You must find out how God wants you to spend your love.
但我已献身上帝 我要终生为上帝服务
But I pledged my life to God. I pledged my life to his service.
我的女儿 如果你爱这个人 并不表示你就要少爱上帝了
My daughter, if you love this man, it doesn't mean you love God less.
这样不行
No.
你必须找出答案
You must find out.
你必须要回去
You must go back.
院长 你不能要求我这样做
You can't ask me to do that.
-拜托你 让我留下 我求求你 -玛丽亚
-Please Let me stay. I beg-- -Maria.
这些墙 并不是用来封锁问题的
These walls were not built to shut out problems.
你必须面对它
You have to face them.
你将要过你本来就应过的生活
You have to live the life you were born to live.
♪ 攀登每一座山 ♪
♪ Climb every mountain ♪
♪ 专心诚意地寻求 ♪
♪ Search high and low ♪
♪ 踏遍每条僻路小径 ♪
♪ Follow every byway ♪
♪ 走过已知的每条路 ♪
♪ Every path you know ♪
♪ 攀登每一座山 ♪
♪ Climb every mountain ♪
♪ 上溯每条溪 ♪
♪ Ford every stream ♪
♪ 追寻每一道彩虹 ♪
♪ Follow every rainbow ♪
♪ 直到找到你的美梦 ♪
♪ Till you find your dream ♪
♪ 这美梦需要你 ♪
♪ A dream that will need ♪
♪ 献出全部的爱 ♪
♪ all the love you can give ♪
♪ 生命的每分每秒 ♪
♪ Every day of your life ♪
♪ 直到地久天长 ♪
♪ For as long as you live ♪
♪ 攀登每一座山 ♪
♪ Climb every mountain ♪
♪ 上溯每条溪 ♪
♪ Ford every stream ♪
♪ 追寻每一道彩虹 ♪
♪ Follow every rainbow ♪
♪ 直到找到你的美梦 ♪
♪ Till you find your dream ♪
♪ 这美梦需要你 ♪
♪ A dream that will need ♪
♪ 献出全部的爱 ♪
♪ all the love you can give ♪
♪ 生命的每分每秒 ♪
♪ Every day of your life ♪
♪ 直到地久天长 ♪
♪ For as long as you live ♪
♪ 攀登每一座山 ♪
♪ Climb every mountain ♪
♪ 上溯每条溪 ♪
♪ Ford every stream ♪
♪ 追寻每一道彩虹 ♪
♪ Follow every rainbow ♪
♪ 直到找到 ♪
♪ Till you find... ♪
♪ 你的美梦 ♪
♪ ... your dream ♪
这样鬼鬼祟祟 不像我的孩子
Now, it's not like my children to be secretive.
我们没有鬼鬼祟祟 爸爸
We're not being secretive, father.
吃饭迟到也不像我的孩子
And it's not like my children to be late for dinner.
-我们忘了时间而已 -是这样吗？
-We lost track of the time. -I see.
好了 谁要第一个告诉我事实 费瑞克？
Who's going to be the first one to tell me the truth? Friedrich.
碧姬塔？莉莎？
Brigitta. Liesl.
爸爸 你懧为我们去哪？
Where do you think we were, father?
如果你不相信我们 那我们去哪 你心里一定有数
If you don't believe us, you must have some idea of where you think we were.
-玛塔？ -是的 爸爸
-Marta. -Yes, father.
你来告诉我
You tell me.
碧姬塔说了 爸爸 我们去采莓子了
Friedrich told you, father. we were berry picking.
-我忘了 你们去采莓子了 -是啊 我们很爱采莓子
-I forgot!You were berry picking. -Yes, we love berry picking.
整个下午？
All afternoon?
-是的 我们采了几千颗 -几千颗？
-We picked thousands. -Thousands?
-满山遍野都是 -哪一种莓？
-They were all over the place. -What kind of berries?
-是蓝莓 -蓝莓
-Blueberries, sir. -Blueberries.
蓝莓的季节还没到耶...
It's too early for blueberries.
-是草莓 -是草莓？
-They were strawberries. -Strawberries?
最近很冷 所以它们变成蓝色了
It's been so cold lately, they turned blue.
很好 把莓子拿给我看
Very well. Show me the berries.
-我们... -这个嘛...
-We... . -Well... .
-快把莓子给我 -我们一个也没了
-Show me the berries you picked. -We don't have them.
一个也没了？ 发生了什么事？
You don't have them? What happened to them?
我们...我们把它们都吃了
-We... . -We ate them.
-你们吃了它们 -是啊 是啊
-You ate them? -Yes!
-很好吃 -非常的好
-They were so Good. -Delicious.
非常好
Very well.
既然你们吃了几千颗的莓子
Since you've obviously stuffed yourselves on thousands of berries...
你们不可能胜子饿了 所以我可以告诉思蜜德
...you can't be hungry anymore, so I'll have to tell Frau Schmidt...
不用煮你们的晚餐
...to skip your dinner.
都是你的错 我们应该老实告诉他
It's your fault. we should have told him the truth.
让他对我们生气
And made him boiling mad at us?
总比饿死好
It's better than starving to death.
我们没有做错什么 我们只是想看她
We didn't do anything wrong. we just wanted to see her.
我的胜子在咕咕叫了
My stomach's making noises.
她们至少该让我们跟她打个招呼
The least they could have done was to let us say hello.
-我在想 不知野草的味道如何... -我觉得糟透了
-I wonder What grass tastes like. -I feel awful.
玛丽亚要觉得愉快些时 她就唱那首歌记得吗？
When Fraülein Maria wanted to feel better she used to sing that song.
我们唱唱看
Let's try it.
♪ 玫瑰上的雨滴 ♪
♪ Raindrops on roses ♪
♪ 小猫的胡须 ♪
♪ And whiskers on kittens ♪
♪ 光亮的铜壶 ♪
♪ Bright copper kettles ♪
♪ 温暖的羊毛手套 ♪
♪ And warm woolen mittens ♪
♪ 有细绳的褐色包装纸 ♪
♪ Brown paper packages tied up with strings ♪
♪ 这些都是我心爱的事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
♪ 为什么我没有感觉比较愉快？ ♪
♪ Why don't I feel better? ♪
♪ 女孩们穿着白衣 ♪
♪ Girls in white dresses ♪
♪ 佩着蓝缎带 ♪
♪ With blue satin sashes ♪
♪ 雪花落在我的鼻子和睫毛上 ♪
♪ Snowflakes that stay On my nose and eyelashes ♪
♪ -银白色的冬天 -玛丽亚 她回来了 ♪
♪ -Silver white winters... ♪ -Fraülein Maria's back!
♪ 融化成为春天 ♪
♪ ... that melt into springs ♪
♪ 这些都是我喜爱的事物 ♪
♪ These are a few of my favorite things ♪
♪ 当狗咬时 当蜜蜂蛰时 ♪
♪ When the dog bites When the bee stings ♪
♪ 当我感觉伤心时 ♪
♪ When I'm feeling sad ♪
♪ 只要想起我最喜爱的事物 ♪
♪ I simply remember my favorite things ♪
♪ 我的心情就不会 ♪
♪ And then I don't feel ♪
♪ 如此糟了 ♪
♪ So bad ♪
-孩子们 看到你们真高兴 -我们也想念你
-Children, I'm so glad to see you. -We missed you.
我想念你们
I missed you.
-寇特 你好吗？ -很饿
-Kurt, how are you? -Hungry.
-葛特儿 你的手指怎么了 -被割了
-What happened to your finger? -It got caught.
-被什么割的？ -我的牙齿
-Caught in what? -Friedrich's teeth.
-莉莎 你好吗？ -还好啦
-Liesl, you all right? -just fair.
-最近有没有电报来？ -什么都没有
-any telegrams been delivered lately? -None at all.
但我在学校学着接受它 学校开学我会很高兴的
But I'm learning to accept it. I'll be glad when school begins.
莉莎 学校不是逃避问题的地方 你必须学着面对问题
Liesl, you can't use school to escape your problems. You have to face them.
我要告诉你们很多事
I have so much to tell you.
我们也有许多事要告诉你
We have things to tell you too.
最重要的是 爸爸要结婚了
The most important thing is that father is going to be married.
结婚？
Married?
是的 是和男爵夫人
Yes, to Baroness Schraeder.
哦 我知道了
Oh, I see.
-哦 爸爸 -看 玛丽亚回来了
Father, look! Fraülein Maria's back!
玛丽亚从修道院回来了
Fraülein Maria's back from the abbey.
晚安 舰长
Good evening, captain.
晚安
Good evening.
好了 大家都进去吃晚餐
Everyone inside for dinner.
晚饭
Dinner!
你不告而别 甚至连小孩们都没道别
You left without saying goodbye. Even to the children.
是我的错 请原谅我
It was wrong of me. Forgive me.
为什么要如此？
Why did you?
请不要问我 反正原因已经不存在了
Please don't ask me. the reason no longer exists.
玛丽亚 你回来了
Fraülein Maria, you've returned.
盖尔 这不是很好吗？
Isn't it wonderful, Georg?
男爵夫人 我祝福你幸福快乐
I wish you every happiness, baroness.
你也是 舰长 孩子们告诉我你们要结婚了
You too, captain. the children say you're to marry.
谢谢你 亲爱的
Thank you, my dear.
你再回来 是要留下吗？
You are back to stay?
只待到下一位老师来为止
Only until arrangements can be made for another governess.
原来你在这里
There you are.
牛肉面包太好吃了
I must speak to cook about the schnitzel.
这会影响我的身材
It is entirely too delicious for my figure.
你在餐桌上没说很多话
And it makes you much too quiet at the dinner table.
是不是酒的关系？
Or was it the wine?
应该是酒的因素
Undoubtedly the wine.
你不知道为了要送你 一件结婚礼物
You have no idea the trouble I'm having...
我费尽了多少心思
...trying to decide on a wedding present for you.
我知道 我说够了
Oh, I know. I'm enough.
但是我要你有不同的礼物
But I do want you to have some little trifle for the occasion.
我首先想到的是钢笔
At first I thought of a fountain pen...
但是你已有一支
...but you've already got one.
然后我想送你一幢法国的别墅
Then I thought perhaps a villa in the south of France...
但是它很难包装起来
...but they are so difficult to gift-wrap.
你觉得游艇如何？
Oh, Georg, how do you feel about yachts?
一艘豪华雅致 可航行地中海的？
A long, sleek one for the Mediterranean...
还是一艘小的 放浴缸里？
...or a tiny one for your bathtub, huh?
-艾莎... -我们要去哪渡蜜月？
-Elsa. -Where to go On our honeymoon?
这可真是个难题了
Now, that's a real problem.
我想在森林里旅行会很棒
A trip around the world would be lovely. and then I said:
但一定会有更好的地方...
Oh, Elsa, there must be someplace better to go.
-不过不用担心 达令 我会... -艾莎
-But don't worry, darling, I'll-- -Elsa.
什么事？盖尔
Yes, Georg.
这样行不通的
It's no use...
你和我
...you and l.
我一直都没有坦诚面对 你和我的关系
I'm being dishonest to both of us...
这对你一点都不公平
...and utterly unfair to you.
-当两个人谈论到婚嫁时... -不要
-When two people talk of marriage-- -No, don't.
不要再说了 拜托你
Don't say another word, please.
你知道 我还在想其他的事
You see, there are other things I've been thinking of.
虽然我喜欢你 但是我真的不懧为你适合我
Fond as I am of you, I really don't think you're the right man for me.
你太独立了 而我...
You're much too independent.
我要一个非常需要我的人
And I need someone who needs me desperately...
或至少非常需要我的钱
...or at least needs my money desperately.
和你在一起的每分钟 我都很快乐 谢谢你
I've enjoyed every moment we've had together and I do thank you for that.
失陪一下 我现在要进去了
Now, if you'll forgive me...
收拾我的行李
...I'll go inside, pack my little bags...
回到我原属的地方 维也纳
...and return to Vienna where I belong.
那边有个人
And somewhere out there...
是位年轻小姐
...is a young lady who, I think...
我想她做不成修女了
...will never be a nun.
亲爱的 再见了
Auf Wiedersehen, darling.
哈啰
Hello.
我想我可能会在这里找到你
I thought I just might find you here.
你有什么事吗？
Was there something you wanted?
没有 没有 请坐下
No, no, no. Sit down, please.
请坐
Please.
我可以吗？
May l?
你知道 我在想 在思索两件事情
You know, I was thinking and I was wondering two things:
为什么你逃回修道院？
Why did you run away to the abbey?
还有 是什么让你回来的？
And what was it that made you come back?
这个嘛 我有责任要完成
Well, I had an obligation to fulfill...
我回来履行的
...and I came back to fulfill it.
只是这样吗？
Is that all?
还有 我想念孩子们
And I missed the children.
是的
Yes.
-只有小孩们？ -不只...是的
-Only the children? -No. yes.
-我不可以想念他们吗？ -喔...当然可以
-Isn't it right that I missed them? -Oh, yes. Yes, of course.
我只是希望 也许你能...
I was only hoping that perhaps you... .
也许你可以...
Perhaps you might... .
什么？
Yes?
嗯...当你离开后
Well, nothing was the same when you were away...
一切都变样了 又不正常了
...and it'll be all wrong again after you leave...
我只是想也许 你会改变心意留下来
...and I just thought perhaps you might change your mind.
我想男爵夫人一定会把 一切的事情都安排得很好
Well, I'm sure the baroness will be able to make things fine for you.
玛丽亚
Maria... .
-再也没有什么男爵夫人了 -没有了吗？
-There isn't going to be any baroness. -There isn't?
没有
No.
我不了解
I don't understand.
我们已经解除婚约了
Well, we've called off our engagement, you see, and--
-很遗憾 -是的 你很难过吗？
-Oh, I'm sorry. -Yes. You are?
-你解除婚约了？ -是的
-You did? -Yes.
你不能和一个人结婚
Well, you can't marry someone when you're...
而心里却爱着另一个人
...in love with someone else...
你能不能...
...can you?
院长常说
The Reverend Mother always says:
当上帝关上一扇门时 在某处 祂会开启另一扇窗
When the Lord closes a door, somewhere He opens a window.
院长还说其他的吗？
What else does the Reverend Mother say?
“你需要寻求你自己的生命”		That you have to look for your life.
这是不是你回来的原因？
Is that why you came back?
我很高兴你找到了
And have you found it...
玛丽亚？
...Maria?
我想我找到了
I think I have.
我知道我已找到了
I know I have.
我爱你
I love you.
这是真的吗？
Oh, can this be happening to me?
♪ 我的童年也许坎坷不顺 ♪
♪ Perhaps I had a wicked childhood ♪
♪ 我的少年期也许悲惨黯淡 ♪
♪ Perhaps I had a miserable youth ♪
♪ 但在这些伤感的过往岁月里 ♪
♪ But somewhere ln my wicked, miserable past ♪
♪ 总有时候真诚存在其中 ♪
♪ There must have been a moment of truth ♪
♪ 而你挺立于此 爱着我 ♪
♪ For here you are standing there loving me ♪
♪ 是否你该如此 ♪
♪ Whether or not you should ♪
♪ 所以在往日的悲欢岁月里 ♪
♪ So somewhere in my youth or childhood ♪
♪ 我一定做了什么好事 ♪
♪ I must have done something good ♪
♪ 真爱不会凭空而来 ♪
♪ Nothing comes from nothing ♪
♪ 善有善报 ♪
♪ Nothing ever could ♪
♪ 所以 在我的过往岁月中 ♪
♪ So somewhere in my youth or childhood ♪
♪ 我一定做了什么好事 ♪
♪ I must have done something good ♪
你知道我是何时开始 爱上你的？
Do you know when I first started loving you?
那天晚餐 你坐在那可笑的松果上
That night at dinner, when you sat on that ridiculous pine cone.
什么？
What?
当你吹着那个傻哨子时 我就爱上你了
I knew the first time you blew that silly whistle.
哦 我的爱！
Oh, my love.
♪ 你挺立于此 爱着我 ♪
♪ For here you are standing there loving me ♪
♪ 是否你该如此 ♪
♪ Whether or not you should ♪
♪ 所以 在我的过往岁月中 ♪
♪ So somewhere in my youth or childhood ♪
♪ 我一定做了什么好事 ♪
♪ I must have done something good ♪
♪ 真爱不会凭空而来 ♪
♪ Nothing comes from nothing ♪
♪ 善有善报 ♪
♪ Nothing ever could ♪
♪ 所以 在我的少年岁月... ♪
♪ So somewhere in my youth... ♪
♪ 或孩提时代... ♪
♪ ...or childhood ♪
♪ 我一定做了些什么 ♪
♪ I must have done something ♪
♪ 做了些什么好事 ♪
♪ Something good ♪
玛丽亚
Maria.
你觉得我该征求谁的同意？
Is there anyone I should go to, to ask permission to marry you?
-为什么我们不问... -孩子们？
-Why don't we ask-- -The children?
♪ 你要如何解决像玛丽亚的问题 ♪
♪ How do you solve a problem like Maria? ♪
♪ 如何将浮云摘下后订牢 ♪
♪ How do you catch a cloud and pin it down? ♪
♪ 你要如何用言语形容她 ♪
♪ How do you find a word that means Maria? ♪
♪ 心浮气躁... ♪
♪ A flibbertigibbet ♪
♪ 骗子、小丑 ♪
♪ A will-o '-the-wisp a clown ♪
♪ 许多事你们想告诉她 ♪
♪ Many a thing you know you'd like to tell her ♪
♪ 许多事她该明了 ♪
♪ Many a thing she ought to understand ♪
♪ 但如何使她停下听你说完 ♪
♪ But how do you make her stay and listen to all you say? ♪
♪ 如何使海浪停留在沙滩上 ♪
♪ How do you keep a wave upon the sand? ♪
♪ 如何解决像玛丽亚的问题 ♪
♪ Oh, how do you solve a problem like Maria? ♪
♪ 如何使月光在掌中停留 ♪
♪ How do you hold a moonbeam ln your hand? ♪
你好
Herr Detweiler!
希特勒万岁 午安 赫尔吉勒
-Heil Hitler. -Oh, Good afternoon, Herr Zeller.
或许你还不知道 我现在是这里的监督
Perhaps you've not heard. I am now the Gauleiter.
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler.
我刚从范崔普家来
I've come from Captain von Trapp's house.
自从两国合并之后
The only one in the area not flying the Third Reich flag...
只有他家不挂德国旗
...since the Anschluss.
-但是我们必须解决那问题 -我不知道...
-But we have dealt with that. -I don't--
管家告诉我会在这找到你
The housekeeper told me that I would find you here.
这是那个女人 唯一留给我的情报
The only thing she'd tell me.
你在找什么情报？
What kind of information are you looking for?
我们要知道舰长何时会回来？
When will the captain return?
他去渡蜜月了 他没和我们联络
Well, he's on his honeymoon trip. He's not been in touch with us.
你要我相信舰长一个多月 没和他的孩子们联络
Am I to believe he hasn't communicated with his children in over a month?
监督 你知道会有多少人
How many men do you know...
他们在渡蜜月时 和他们的孩子联络？
...who communicate with their children while honeymooning?
当他回来时 我们希望他接受新政府的职位
Upon his return, he'll fill his proper position in the new order.
当然了...我可以向你恭禧
Naturally. and may I congratulate you...
你的人们决定允许今晚 我们可以举行音乐节庆
...and your people in allowing the festival to go on tonight as planned.
为何他们会不允准？ 奥国什么都没改变
Why should it not go on? Nothing in Austria has changed.
唱歌和音乐可宣告世界
Singing and music will show this to the world.
奥国依然如昔
Austria is the same.
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler.
走吧 孩子们 我们回家去
Come, let's go home.
-为何他这么凶？ -达令 这些日子大家都很凶
-Why was he so cross? -Everybody's cross these days.
也许是旗上的黑蜘蛛 使人们紧张起来
Maybe the flag with the black spider makes people nervous.
-爸爸是不是有麻烦了？ -他不会的
-Will father be in trouble? -He doesn't have to be.
这些日子来最重要的是 和大家和睦相处
The thing to do is to get along with everybody.
我要你们记住 尤其在今晚的演唱会上
Remember that tonight at the concert.
今晚我们真的要 在一大堆人面前唱歌？
Are we really going to sing before a lot of people?
当然 看范崔普家庭音乐 这上面是名字
Look. the von Trapp Family Singers:
莉莎、费瑞克、露易莎、碧姬塔 寇特、玛塔、葛特儿
Liesl, Friedrich, Louisa, Brigitta, Kurt, Marta and Gretl.
-为什么我总是排在最后？ -因为你是最重要的
-Why am I always last? -Because you are the most important.
我们走吧
There we go.
麦伯伯 你确定爸爸 会准许我们公开演唱
Are you sure father will approve of our singing in public?
他会很高兴而引以为傲的
He'll be pleased and proud.
-莉莎 你觉得如此吗？ -你们不信任我吗？
-Liesl, do you think so? -Don't you trust me?
不信任
No.
你们是很聪明的女孩
You're a very intelligent girl.
莉莎...
Liesl. Liesl!
劳夫
Rolf!
劳夫 很高兴见到你 已经...
I'm so glad to see you. It's been su--
午安
Good afternoon.
请你把这电报交给你爸爸
Give this to your father as soon as he's home.
-他正在渡蜜月呢 -我知道
-He's on his honeymoon. -I know.
-你知道？ -做这行的 样样都要知道
-you do? -We make It our business to know all.
-谁是我们？ -他看电报就知道
-Who's "we"? -See that he gets it.
-这是什么？ -是从柏林来的电报
-What is it? -It's a telegram from Berlin.
你今晚不要来亲自交给他吗？
Don't you want to deliver it yourself?
我今晚有更重要的事
I'm occupied with more important matters.
你爸爸如果知轻重 最好合作点
And your father had better be too.
但是 劳夫...
But, Rolf!
爸爸...
Father!
-我们没想到你们这么早回来 -哈啰！哈啰！
-We didn't expect you so soon. -Hello, hello!
我们不知道你这么早就会回来
We didn't expect you home until next week!
-有带东西给我们吗？ -哈啰 你好吗？
-Did you bring souvenirs from Paris? -Hello!How are you?
你们为什么没有打电报给我们？
Why didn't you call us?
我们试过了 但是不通
We couldn't get through.
国旗和我没有关系
I had nothing to do with that.
我们已经尽量赶回来了
We came back as fast as we could.
我们很想念你们
Well, well, well! we missed you!
-我们很想你们 -我们也很想你们
-We missed you! -We missed kissing you.
我们想念你们早上的噪音
We missed all the noise in the morning.
-最想念的是你们 -你们回来得正巧
-Mostly, we missed hearing you sing. -Oh, you came back just in time.
看这个 玛丽亚
Look, Fraülein Maria--
我是说妈妈
I mean Mother.
我们今晚要去音乐会
We're going to sing in the festival tonight.
我们度过了很美好的时光喔
We've been having a lovely time!
我们练习了一天
We've been rehearsing all--
惊喜 惊喜
Surprise! Surprise!
好了 里面有令你们惊喜的东西
Surprises for you on the terrace.
我们到里面去谈这个
We'll talk about this.
盖尔 我本想要告诉你 但是你不在 我只有自作主张了
I would've told you but you were away. I had to make a last-minute decision.
我运气好 能让他们参加
I was fortunate to enter them at all.
他们会成为话题的 试想一个家庭中的蒳个小孩
They'll be the talk of the festival. Imagine, seven children in one family!
麦斯！
Max!
我记得我以前 就对我家中小孩
Somehow I recall having made it quite clear to you...
在外面演唱的事说得很清楚
...how I feel about my family singing in public!
但是委员会听过他们唱 非常的感动
The committee was enchanted.
-他们说了什么？ -“从没听过这样热情澎湃的歌声”
-What Did They say? -I have never heard such enthusiasm.
-达令 就一次好不好？ -绝对不可能
-Don't you think just this once--? -Absolutely out of the question.
-盖尔 这是为了奥国 -奥国？
-Georg, this is for Austria. -for Austria?
-已经没有奥国 -但是德奥合并会很和平的
-There is no Austria! -But the Anschluss was peaceful.
-这是很好的 -很好？！
-Let's at least be grateful for that. -Grateful?
你知道吗？麦斯
You know, Max...
有时候我不知道是否了解你
...sometimes I don't believe I know you.
爸爸 我忘了
Father, I forgot.
这是给你的
This is for you.
玛丽亚 至少他必须假装 和这些人合作
Maria, he has got to at least pretend to work with these people.
你必须说服他
You must convince him.
我不能要求他听我的话
Max, I can't ask him to be less than he is.
那么我和他谈 如果孩子们不在节庆上唱歌...
Then I'll talk to him. If the children don't sing, well...
对奥国会有影响的
...it will be a reflection on Austria.
对我也没有好处
Oh, I know. It wouldn't do me any good either.
妈 这听起来真好
Mother? that sounds so nice.
-我喜欢叫你妈 -我喜欢听你叫
-I like calling you "Mother." -I like hearing it.
你很爱爸爸 我看得出来
You love father very much. I can tell you do.
非常爱他
Very much.
妈 当你懧为你爱某个人时 你要怎么办？
Mother, what do you do when you think you love someone?
我是说当你不再爱某人 或者说他不再爱你时...
I mean, when you stop loving someone or he stops loving you?
你会哭一场
Well, you cry a little.
等待太阳出来
Then you wait for the sun to come out.
每次都可以这样的
It always does.
有许多事情我懧为我应该知道 但我却不知道
There are so many things I think I should know but I don't.
-真的不知道 -怎么说？
-I really don't. -How can you?
有时我觉得世界末日近了
Sometimes I feel the world is ending.
-你觉得这刚开始 -是的
-Then you feel it's just beginning? -Yes!
我以前也这么觉得 对你 一切会很好的
It was that way with me. and for you it will be just as wonderful.
你真的懧为如此？
Do you really think so?
♪ 你16岁 快17岁了 ♪
♪ When you're 16 going on 17 ♪
♪ 人生才要开始 ♪
♪ Waiting for life to start ♪
♪ 有个好人触动你的心灵 ♪
♪ Somebody kind who touches your mind ♪
♪ 你突然感到心悸 ♪
♪ Will suddenly touch your heart ♪
♪ 当发生时 ♪
♪ When that happens ♪
♪ 真的发生时 ♪
♪ After it happens ♪
♪ 一切都改变了 ♪
♪ Nothing is quite the same ♪
♪ 我仿佛知道 ♪
♪ Somehow I know ♪
♪ 每当他叫我时 ♪
♪ I'll jump up and go ♪
♪ 心中小鹿就乱跳 ♪
♪ If ever he calls my name ♪
♪ 你梦想的生活 ♪
♪ Gone are your old ideas of life ♪
♪ 很想实现 ♪
♪ the old ideas grow dim ♪
♪ 而你却成为人了 ♪
♪ Lo and behold You're someone's wife ♪
♪ 你属于他 ♪
♪ and you belong to him ♪
♪ 你会以为这种过程 ♪
♪ You may think this kind of adventure ♪
♪ 不会发生在你身上 ♪
♪ Never may come to you ♪
♪ 亲爱的你16岁 快17岁了 ♪
♪ Darling, 16 going on 17 ♪
♪ 耐心等待... ♪
♪ Wait a year... ♪
♪ -我会耐心等待... -耐心等待... ♪
♪ -I'll wait a year -...or two ♪
♪ 耐心等待... ♪
♪ just wait a year... ♪
♪ 他来临 ♪
♪ ...or two ♪
莉莎
Liesl.
什么事情？
What is it?
柏林
Berlin.
柏林派我一个海军的官
They've offered me a commission.
他们要求我马上上任
I've been requested to accept immediately...
明天到柏林里麦基地报到
...and report to their naval base at Bremerhaven tomorrow.
我就知道这种事会发生 没料到这么快
I knew this would happen. I didn't think it would be so soon.
拒绝的话 全家性命不保
To refuse them would be fatal for all of us.
参加了 会更难想像
And joining them would be unthinkable.
叫小孩们都过来
Get the children all together.
什么都不要说 让他们打包好行囊
Don't say anything to worry them. just get them ready.
我们必须离开奥国
We've got to get out of Austria...
还有这个房子
...and this house...
今晚
...tonight.
今晚你们不唱了
This strains my back and breaks my heart...
真是让我伤心难过
...when I think of the children missing the festival.
你宣布的时候 我们就越过边界了
By your announcement we'll be over the border.
我希望你会感激我所做的牺牲
Do you appreciate the sacrifice I'm making?
你没有选择
You have no choice.
我知道 这是为何我这样做
I know. That's why I'm making it.
爸爸为何不发动引擎
Why doesn't father turn the motor on?
因为他不要任何人听到
Because he doesn't want anyone to hear us.
管家们会说什么？
What will Frau Schmidt and Franz say?
他们可以老实回答 有人问他们时 他们什么都不知道
They'll be able to answer honestly they didn't know anything.
-我们会再回来吗？ -莉莎 我希望会有这一天的
-will we be coming back here? -Someday, Liesl. I do hope someday.
爸爸和麦伯伯 要一直推车到瑞士吗？
Are father and Uncle Max going to push the car all the way to Switzerland?
舰长 你的车是不是有毛病？
Something wrong with your car, captain?
是的 事实上 车子无法启动
Yes, we couldn't get it started.
卡尔
Karl.
替舰长把车修好好让其启动
Fix Captain von Trapp's car so that it will start.
很好的车啊
Excellent, Karl.
我没问你和你的家人要到哪？
I've not asked you where you and your family are going.
你也没问我 我为何在这？
Nor have you asked me why I'm here.
我想我们两个都没什么好奇心
Apparently we both suffer from a deplorable lack of curiosity.
你接到柏林来的电报 你并没有回覆
You never answered the telegram...
这封电报叫你去海军基地报到
...from the Admiral of the Navy of the Third Reich.
电报的内容
I was under the impression, Herr Zeller...
是不可以让任何人窥看
...that the contents of telegrams in Austria are private!
至少在奥国是这样
At least, the Austria I know.
我奉命
I have my orders...
今晚带你去基地
...to take you to Bremerhaven tonight...
接受你的职务
...where you will accept your commission.
恐怕恕难从命
I'm afraid that's going to be quite impossible.
你知道...
You see, we...
我们全部的家庭
...all of us, the entire family, will be...
今晚要在音乐会上演唱
...singing in the festival tonight.
事实上 这就是我们要出去的原因
As a matter of fact, we're going now.
不可能现在让他们失望
We couldn't possibly let them down now.
-我希望我们不会迟到 -是的
-I just hope we're not too late. -Yes.
你要我相信你堂堂一位舰长
You ask me to believe that you, Captain von Trapp...
要去演唱会唱歌
...are singing in a concert?
相信我 这会是最棒的表演
Believe me, it will be a performance beyond anything even I've dreamt of.
吉勒 像你一样 我们两个都是身怀绝技的
Like you, Herr Zeller, l, too, am a man of hidden talents.
是的
Yes.
这是节目单
Here, program.
上面只有孩子的名字
It says only the names of the children.
上面说范崔普家演唱
It says the von Trapp Family Singers...
而我是范崔普家的家长 不是吗？
...and I am the head of the von Trapp family, am I not?
穿着这些旅行装？
And these travel clothes that you're all wearing?
是我们的习惯
Our costumes, naturally.
今晚天气不好 穿礼服会对孩子的嗓子有影响
This night air is not good for the children's voices.
稍微延迟执行命令并不严重
Well, a slight delay in my orders will not be serious.
好吧
Therefore...
你们去唱吧
...you will sing.
你们全部都要唱
You will all sing.
这只是我希望
But only because that's what I want.
这表示奥国一切未改
It will demonstrate that nothing in Austria has changed.
你们唱完后
And when you have finished singing...
你们的舰长就要跟我走
...you, Captain von Trapp, will be taken to Bremerhaven.
现在 你们上车吧
Now, if you will all get into your car...
我们要护送 范崔普家的歌手去演唱会
...we will escort the von Trapp Family Singers to the festival.
吉勒 用不着护送
No escort will be necessary.
舰长 我们乐意如此
Necessary? a pleasure, captain.
而且我们不希望你们迷了路
After all, we would not want you to get lost in the crowds.
是吗？
Would we?
是的
No.
♪ SEW是穿针缝衣服 ♪
♪ Sew, a needle pulling thread ♪
♪ LA是SO的小跟班 ♪
♪ La, a note to follow sew ♪
♪ TEA是茶配果酱面包 ♪
♪ Tea, a drink with jam and bread ♪
♪ 茶配果酱面包... ♪
♪ A drink with jam and bread ♪
♪ Tea with jam Jam and bread ♪
♪ -配果酱 -A B C ♪
♪ -With jam -A, B, C ♪
♪ -配果酱 -DOREMI ♪
♪ -With jam -Do-re-mi ♪
♪ 茶配果酱面包 ♪
♪ Tea with jam and bread ♪
♪ With jam and bread ♪
♪ -配果酱 -配果酱 ♪
♪ With jam With jam... ♪
♪ 和面包... ♪
♪ ...and bread ♪
各位奥国兄弟们
My fellow Austrians...
或许我会有一段时间 见不到你们了
...I shall not be seeing you again, perhaps for a very long time.
现在我要为你们而唱
I would like to sing for you now...
一首情歌
...a love song.
我知道你们会分享此爱
I know you share this love.
我祈求你们永远不会让它逝去
I pray that you will never let it die.
♪ 薄雪草 ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ 每日清晨你向我打招呼 ♪
♪ Every morning you greet me ♪
♪ 小又白 ♪
♪ Small and white ♪
♪ 洁而亮 ♪
♪ Clean and bright ♪
♪ 你很高兴遇见我 ♪
♪ You look happy to meet me ♪
♪ 雪白的花朵 ♪
♪ Blossom of snow ♪
♪ 愿你绽放、茁壮 ♪
♪ May you bloom and grow ♪
♪ 永远盛开 永远成长 ♪
♪ Bloom and grow forever ♪
♪ 薄雪草 ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ 永远祝福我的故乡 ♪
♪ Bless my homeland forever ♪
♪ 薄雪草 ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ Edel.... ♪
♪ 小又白 ♪
♪ Small and white ♪
♪ 洁而亮 ♪
♪ Clean and bright ♪
♪ 你很高兴遇见我 ♪
♪ You look happy to meet me ♪
♪ 雪白的花朵 ♪
♪ Blossom of snow ♪
♪ 愿你绽放、茁壮 ♪
♪ May you bloom and grow ♪
♪ 永远盛开 永远成长 ♪
♪ Bloom and grow forever ♪
♪ 薄雪草 ♪
♪ Edelweiss ♪
♪ 永远祝福我的故乡 ♪
♪ Bless my homeland forever ♪
我想是会行得通
I think it'll work.
我会想念你们大家
I shall miss all of you.
和可以赢得的奖金
I shall miss the money I could have made with you.
谢谢各位先生女士 谢谢
Thank you, ladies and gentlemen.
比赛就要结束
The competition has come to its conclusion...
还不知道我们的结果如何
...except, we don't know yet what that conclusion will be.
当裁判在做出决定之前
And while the judges arrive at their decision...
我允许再给范崔普家一次演出
...I have been given permission to offer you an encore.
这是范崔普家庭最后一次合唱
This will be the last opportunity the von Trapps will have...
此后 大概许久不会有机会了
...of singing together for a long, long time.
甚至现在
Even now, officials are waiting in this auditorium...
官员正等着护送范崔普舰长
...to escort Captain von Trapp to his new command...
向新司令报到
...in the naval forces of the Third Reich.
所以各位先生女士 范崔普家人再一次
And so, ladies and gentlemen, the family von Trapp again...
向你们告别
...to bid you farewell.
♪ 忧愁的钟声来自大厅 ♪
♪ There's a sad sort of clanging from the clock in the hall ♪
♪ 钟声也响起了 ♪
♪ and the bells in the steeple too ♪
♪ 在孩子们卧室里 一只滑稽的小鸟 ♪
♪ and up in the nursery an absurd little bird ♪
♪ 伸出舌头来道“咕咕” ♪
♪ Is popping out to say "coo-coo" ♪
♪ 咕咕 ♪
♪ Coo-coo ♪
♪ 他们很遗憾地催我们离开 ♪
♪ Regretfully they tell us ♪
♪ 又坚定地告诉我们 ♪
♪ But firmly they compel us ♪
♪ 要我们向大家 ♪
♪ To say goodbye ♪
♪ 道晚安 ♪
♪ To you ♪
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell Auf Wiedersehen, good night ♪
♪ 我不愿离开这个美景 ♪
♪ we hate to go and miss this pretty sight ♪
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell Auf Wiedersehen, adieu ♪
♪ 大家再见 ♪
♪ Adieu, adieu To you and you and you ♪
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell Auf Wiedersehen, goodbye ♪
♪ 我临去叹息 ♪
♪ we flit, we float ♪
♪ 说声再见 ♪
♪ we fleetly flee, we fly ♪
♪ 别了 再见 珍重晚安 ♪
♪ So long, farewell Auf Wiedersehen, goodbye ♪
♪ 太阳已安眠！我也必须睡觉！ ♪
♪ the sun has gone to bed and so must I ♪
♪ 别了 ♪
♪ Goodbye ♪
♪ 再见 ♪
♪ 珍重再见 ♪
♪ Goodbye ♪
各位先生女士 我手上有了裁判的决定
Ladies and gentlemen, I have here the decision of our distinguished judges.
我们由第三名报起
We will start with the award for third prize.
我有幸向你们宣布裁判
For this honor, the judges have named...
第三名独唱得主
...the first soloist of the choir of St. Agatha's Church in Murback.
是史瓦格小姐
Fraülein Schweiger.
第二名是图比合唱团
Second prize to the Toby Reiser Quintet.
第一名奥国最高荣誉奖
And the first prize, the highest honor in all Austria...
范崔普家庭合唱团
...the von Trapp Family Singers.
范崔普家庭
The family von Trapp.
他们走了
They're gone!
跟我来
Come with me.
快点 快点
Quickly, quickly.
我有个地方可躲
I have a place you can hide.
慢慢来...
Slowly, slowly.
把大门打开
Open this gate.
晚安
Good evening.
女人 快一点
Hurry up, woman.
两个人到里面去
Two men in there.
六个人去那里
Six of you cover the yard.
你们两人去走廊
You two, cover the corridor.
院长 没想到连累了修道院
Reverend Mother, we didn't realize we put the abbey in this danger.
不 玛丽亚 你们来是对的
No, Maria, it was right for you to come here.
我们想借用你们的车
We thought we might borrow your car.
你们用不上车了
I'm afraid our car will do you no good now.
我听说无线电说
I've been listening to the wires.
边界被封锁了
The borders have just been closed.
好吧 边界被封锁了
All right, if the borders are closed...
那么我们开车到山里 再徒步过去
...then we'll drive up into the hills and go over the mountains on foot.
-小孩们？ -我们可以帮他们
-The children-- -We'll help them.
爸爸 我们不需要帮助
We can do it without help, father.
玛丽亚
Maria.
你不会孤独无助的 记住
You will not be alone. Remember:
上帝说 我会睁开双眼协助的
"I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills from whence cometh my help."
是的 院长
Yes, Mother.
-我好害怕 -我也是
-I'm scared. -Me too.
上帝与你同在
God be with you.
-妈 -是的
-Mother. -Yes?
我们唱歌会有帮助吗？
Would it help if we sang about our favorite things?
不 达令 这是帮不上忙的一次
No, darling. This is one time it would not help.
你必须很安静 紧抱着我
You must be very quiet. Hold tight to me.
走吧 我们到屋顶看看
Let's try the roof.
劳夫 求求你
Rolf, please.
不要 等一下
No, wait.
玛丽亚
Maria.
孩子们
Children.
我们要的只是你
It's you we want, not them.
把那个放下
Put that down.
不准动 否则我就开枪
Not another move, or I'll shoot.
你只是个孩子
You're only a boy.
-你并不是他们的人 -站在原地
-You don't really belong to them. -Stay where you are.
跟我们逃吧
Come away with us.
现在还来得及
Before it's too late.
你再进一步 我就杀了你
Not another step. I'll kill you.
-你把枪给我 劳夫 -你有没有听到
-you give that to me, Rolf. -Did you hear me?
我会杀了你
I'll kill you.
劳夫
Rolf.
你永远不会跟他们一样
You'll never be one of them.
中尉
Lieutenant!
他们在这里
They're here!
他们在这里 中尉
They're here, lieutenant!
院长
Reverend Mother.
我有罪
I have sinned.
院长 我也是
I too, Reverend Mother.
孩子们 是什么罪？
What is this sin, my children?
♪ 这美梦需要你 ♪
♪ A dream that will need ♪
♪ 献出全部的爱 ♪
♪ all the love you can give ♪
♪ 生命的每分每秒 ♪
♪ Every day of your life ♪
♪ 直到地久天长 ♪
♪ For as long as you live ♪
♪ 攀登每一座山 ♪
♪ Climb every mountain ♪
♪ 上溯每条溪 ♪
♪ Ford every stream ♪
♪ 追寻每一道彩虹 ♪
♪ Follow every rainbow ♪
♪ 直到找到 ♪
♪ Till you find... ♪
♪ 你的美梦 ♪
♪ ... your dream... ♪